<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elisabeth Gray</title>
    <description>A repository of personal and academic work created by Elisabeth Gray</description>
    <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.elisabethgray.me//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 16:47:03 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 16:47:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the culmination point of my Master of Science in Global Technology and Development at Arizona State University. As such, I&amp;#39;ve been asked to analyze what this all means in terms of social media and social movements beyond the Arab uprisings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among its many uses, social media has acted as a platform for individuals to vocalize their opposition toward repressive political structures. It has afforded them a voice of dissent toward mainstream media sources—in many places considered to be controlled or manipulated by the state government—and toward government leaders themselves. As such, social media has acted as a democratizing agent by allowing the dissatisfied or disenfranchised to bypass sometimes elaborate barriers of censorship or bureaucracy in order to be heard by a broader audience. It will continue to be used in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week I learned that a Baltimore activist, Joseph Kent, had been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/videos/us/2015/04/29/ctn-live-cuomo-baltimore-joseph-kent-arrested.cnn&quot;&gt;taken by police&lt;/a&gt; while trying to get people out after curfew to disperse. The reaction on Twitter was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.salon.com/2015/04/29/where_is_joseph_kent_social_media_erupts_after_cameras_capture_activists_suspicious_looking_arrest/&quot;&gt;immediate and intense&lt;/a&gt;; tweets referencing #JosephKent demanded answers for his apprehension and his wellbeing. On April 30th, he was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbsnews.com/news/joseph-kent-keep-protesting-but-positively/&quot;&gt;released&lt;/a&gt;. The attention drawn to his arrest on social media is attributed to his swift release. This illustrates the speed of accountability that social media offers. This is where efforts toward long-lasting change &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/05/beyond-hashtag-activism/391988/&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is being taken seriously by political institutions; the Pentagon has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/environment/earth-insight/2014/jun/12/pentagon-mass-civil-breakdown&quot;&gt;invested in research&lt;/a&gt; on the dynamics of social movements, and Egyptian police are looking to improve their &lt;a href=&quot;http://mashable.com/2014/06/21/egyptian-social-media-monitoring-first/&quot;&gt;social media-monitoring software&lt;/a&gt;. The ease with which oppressive governments can and have used technology to monitor and/or oppress citizens presents another angle which needs to be considered when anticipating the future of social media and social movements. The tactics used in the Arab uprisings and elsewhere may not be as effective now that governments know better what to expect and are better prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is an invaluable resource for coordinated efforts, spreading messages quickly and efficiently among individuals, but once a synchronization of opinion is accomplished, organized actions must follow. The speed at which social media facilitated a global conversation about freedom and dignity in the MENA region left many youth with the expectation of equally quick changes to their political institutions. That has been a disappointment across all three countries that I studied, but it shouldn&amp;#39;t discourage continued efforts toward more inclusive institutions. Social media&amp;#39;s structure is agile in a way that most government structures are not. Efforts to engage communities where they live—virtually and physically—will need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media in the general sense has been a part of human history for far longer than Facebook and Twitter have existed; it&amp;#39;s unlikely that it will go away anytime soon. I can&amp;#39;t predict the outcome of the Arab uprisings any more effectively than I can predict the outcome of the protests occurring in Baltimore today. What I can assert with a reasonable amount of certainty is that change will be enacted by those who can motivate others to actively and personally engage—to build community groups, to unite in protest, to speak out in solidarity, to petition representatives, and to engage in what has become a global dialogue about inequality and government corruption. These are common factors for many of the uprisings following those in the MENA region:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/nov/15/lessons-from-iceland-people-power&quot;&gt;Iceland&amp;#39;s  revolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.occupytogether.org/&quot;&gt;Occupy movements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-22924886&quot;&gt;Gezi Park protests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/08/13/us/ferguson-missouri-town-under-siege-after-police-shooting.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;Ferguson protests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://blacklivesmatter.com/&quot;&gt;Black Lives Matter Movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vox.com/2014/9/29/6865681/one-chart-that-explains-the-protests-in-hong-kong&quot;&gt;Hong Kong&amp;#39;s protests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is but one component of revolutionary change. What determines the fate of a people is determined in the streets, in the courthouses, in the classrooms, in the workplaces. Change occurs in the places where we meet each other eye to eye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/05/01/smau-analysis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/05/01/smau-analysis/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Conclusion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In his book, &lt;em&gt;Writing on the wall: Social media, the first 2,000 years&lt;/em&gt;, Standage is quick to point out that &amp;quot;social media does not merely connect us to each other today—it also links us to the past&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#standage&quot;&gt;(Standage, 2013, p. 89)&lt;/a&gt;. Protestors have used media devices to disseminate messages of solidarity and of dissent for generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Arab uprisings, the ability with which citizens united and coordinated their message was undoubtedly facilitated by social media, but the experience gained from organized movements of the past was imperative to their efficacy. The main conclusions that can be drawn from this project are that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media did not cause the Arab uprisings.&lt;/strong&gt; Underlying grievances of corruption, repression, economic disparity, and censorship triggered them. Social media empowered citizens to find their voice as a people (&lt;em&gt;sha&amp;#39;b&lt;/em&gt;). It enabled them to organize and to expose injustice. It spread their messages &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt;. And most importantly, it garnered a broad audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media played a significant role in the Arab uprisings.&lt;/strong&gt; It enabled a &amp;quot;synchronization of opinion&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#standage&quot;&gt;(Standage, 2013, p. 1044)&lt;/a&gt; across the MENA region as dissatisfied individuals identified common offenses made by their governments and established a unified demand for dignity and freedom from oppression. Solidarity was key. Politics of dominance and exclusion don&amp;#39;t work, as can be seen most clearly in Libya today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media is more than a tool.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#39;s a platform for cultural and political expression which can be used to augment the voices of a movement. Corrupt institutions fear the discovery of this voice, which can be seen in the history of censorship and repression in Tunisia, Egypt, and Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facilitation of communication and political expression was critical to the Arab uprisings. It offered citizens of repressive countries a window to the outside and allowed them to learn from people who had experience holding peaceful political protests or solicit help from those who were connected to large audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media is not a panacea.&lt;/strong&gt; The ease and speed with which a message can be disseminated is social media&amp;#39;s source of power and its greatest weakness. Ordinary individuals can speak for themselves rather than relying upon media conglomerates to do it for them, but these benefits don&amp;#39;t come without consequences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morozov notes, the Internet “penetrates and reshapes all walks of political life, not just the ones conducive to democratization.” Anyone who hopes that the Internet will spread Western-style liberal democracy must bear in mind that the same digital tools have also been embraced by campaigners with very different aims, such as Hezbollah in Lebanon and ultra-right-wing nationalist groups in Russia &lt;a href=&quot;#standage&quot;&gt;(Standage, 2013, p. 4097)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media moves so quickly that it sets up an &lt;em&gt;expectation&lt;/em&gt; of equally fast results. As can be seen in Egypt and Libya, rapid changes can&amp;#39;t necessarily be equated with permanent ones. Tunisians are learning that changing the infrastructure of a country takes a lot of time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While active citizenship and civil participation among young Tunisians is critical to sustaining the country’s positive socio-economic momentum and achieving political stability, very few engage in any form of political participation, except mobilizing for demonstrations. In fact, youth activism is done in an ad-hoc manner with social media as the mobilizing tool, outside the formally established civil and political institutions &lt;a href=&quot;#wb-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“World Bank Report: Young People in Tunisia Still Frustrated by Social and Economic Obstacles,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be discouraging, but inaction isn&amp;#39;t an effective alternative. The consequences of inaction impact more than just those in the MENA region—refugees are flocking to European Union countries&amp;#39; shores to escape violence and poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media adds complexity.&lt;/strong&gt; As more and more voices enter the arena, it can be difficult to identify a single message. Greater freedom of expression is extended without bias, so &amp;quot;bad ideas will proliferate as well as good ones,&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#standage&quot;&gt;(Standage, 2013, p. 4119)&lt;/a&gt; but this also means that divergent messages can be debated out in the open and acknowledged rather than ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complexity of this system can also cause us to be distracted by events rather than the root of an issue. &amp;quot;We live in an exaggerated present—we pay too much attention to recent experience and too little attention to the past, focusing on current events rather than long term behavior&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#meadows&quot;&gt;(Meadows &amp;amp; Wright, 2008, p. 1934)&lt;/a&gt;. This is why it was important to look at the history of Tunisia, Egypt, and Libya when trying to understand social media&amp;#39;s role in the Arab uprisings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media isn&amp;#39;t going away.&lt;/strong&gt; System dynamics scientist Donella Meadows said that &amp;quot;self-organization is such a basic property of living systems that even the most overbearing power structure can never fully kill it, although in the name of law and order, self-organization can be suppressed for long, barren, cruel, boring periods&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#meadows&quot;&gt;(Meadows &amp;amp; Wright, 2008, p. 1402)&lt;/a&gt;. The social media of today—Twitter, Facebook, and the like—are the latest iteration of self-organization in humanity, but they are not likely to be the last. As we learn, diversify, and increase in complexity, new communication and organizational systems will develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this all matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a difficult subject to get people to engage with me on, but that reinforces a fundamental point of the project: &lt;strong&gt;social media doesn&amp;#39;t motivate change in and of itself. We are motivated by the things we &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading a lot about the protests against police brutality toward people of color. As I write, protests are taking place because of the suspicious death of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/04/the-mysterious-death-of-freddie-gray/391119/&quot;&gt;Freddie Gray&lt;/a&gt; after being arrested by Baltimore police. This morning, I came across this music video produced for Run the Jewels&amp;#39; song, Close Your Eyes (&lt;strong&gt;warning&lt;/strong&gt;: strong language is used):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PkGwI7nGehA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the video played out, tears began—and would not stop—streaming down my face. Even now as I think about it, I am emotionally affected by the message of the video. You can read the full director&amp;#39;s statement on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.runthejewels.net/&quot;&gt;Run the Jewels&amp;#39; site&lt;/a&gt;, but here&amp;#39;s what stood out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it was important to write a story that didn’t paint a simplistic portrait of the characters of the Cop and Kid. They&amp;#39;re not stereotypes. They&amp;#39;re people - complex, real people and, as such, the power had to shift between them at certain points throughout the story...I believe that it is important that the way we feel when we see these events in real life has an effect on us. That we resonate with what we know to be right and we don&amp;#39;t numb ourselves out so those feelings can simply be swept away, we must confront them and take some action, however small, or we’ll be stuck in the same cycle of violence and hate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is not to provide answers to the cause of the Arab uprisings as much as it is to open up a dialogue about the many faces and forms of injustice; social media is a platform which can be used to make others aware of injustices and unite against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking differently about the struggle for dignity and identifying it as a human right is the first step toward taking action to combat injustice. You don&amp;#39;t have to go to another country to make a difference in this. That struggle for dignity is happening in the US, as well, and the world is watching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Power &amp;amp; tyranny are different. In some countries like US, police are seemingly powerful but they kill innocents. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/FreddieGray?src=hash&quot;&gt;#FreddieGray&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RekiaBoyd?src=hash&quot;&gt;#RekiaBoyd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Khamenei.ir (@khamenei_ir) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/khamenei_ir/status/592259521554165760&quot;&gt;April 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The greatest threat to the U.S. is not ISIS or Russia.. But their racist roots!! people are waking up and they don&amp;#39;t like it!! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/FreddieGray?src=hash&quot;&gt;#FreddieGray&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; عبد العزيز الفريدي (@AzozAlfuraydi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AzozAlfuraydi/status/592171048445026306&quot;&gt;April 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Patriots&amp;quot; are supposed to resist their oppressors. It&amp;#39;s their God-given right. But only if they&amp;#39;re white. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/FreddieGray?src=hash&quot;&gt;#FreddieGray&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Imani Gandy (@AngryBlackLady) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AngryBlackLady/status/592339784179142657&quot;&gt;April 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another critical step in combatting injustice is speaking out against it. Maryam Al Khawaja spoke clearly on the consequences of silence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The governments will continue to try and silence people. In Syria, Yemen, Egypt, and Bahrain, they will continue to torture, detain, use excessive force, and kill, as long as the people and political leaders of this world choose to stay silent. They will continue to kill their citizens until Western governments realize that their real interest lies in countries with real democracies, not authoritarian regimes. Until they realize that the best way to create stability is by including people and treating them like citizens, not by silencing them and tying their hands to provide a fake calm in the country &lt;a href=&quot;#al-khawaja&quot;&gt;(Al Khawaja, 2012, p. 780)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actions we do or do not take against inequality communicate much more about our values than mere words do. Don&amp;#39;t be silent, and be sure to back up what you say matters with actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
&amp;quot;Sitting at home and just following us on news or Facebook leads to our humiliation….if you stay at home, then you deserve all that’s being done to you and you will be guilty before your nation and your people…never say there’s no hope! Hope disappears only when you say there’s no hope…God says that He &amp;#39;will not change the condition of a people until they change what is in themselves.&amp;#39;&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SgjIgMdsEuk&quot;&gt;Asmaa Mahfouz&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;standage&quot;&gt;Standage, T. (2013). &lt;i&gt;Writing on the wall: Social media, the first 2,000 years&lt;/i&gt; (Kindle). Bloomsbury Publishing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;castells&quot;&gt;Castells, M. (2013). &lt;i&gt;Networks of Outrage and Hope: Social Movements in the Internet Age&lt;/i&gt; (Kindle). Wiley.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levine&quot;&gt;LeVine, M. (2015, January). Tunisia still on the brink. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2015/01/tunisia-still-brink-2015113113441123913.html&quot;&gt;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2015/01/tunisia-still-brink-2015113113441123913.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wb-tunisia&quot;&gt;World Bank Report: Young People in Tunisia Still Frustrated by Social and Economic Obstacles. (2014, October). World Bank. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2014/10/02/world-bank-report-young-people-tunisia-frustrated-social-economic-obstacles&quot;&gt;http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2014/10/02/world-bank-report-young-people-tunisia-frustrated-social-economic-obstacles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;meadows&quot;&gt;Meadows, D. H., &amp;amp; Wright, D. (2008). &lt;i&gt;Thinking in Systems: A Primer&lt;/i&gt; (Kindle). Chelsea Green Publishing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;al-khawaja&quot;&gt;Al Khawaja, M. (2012). Another Flight. In M. Alhassen &amp;amp; A. Shihab-Eldin (Eds.), &lt;i&gt;Demanding Dignity: Young Voices from the Front Lines of the Arab Revolutions (I SPEAK FOR MYSELF)&lt;/i&gt; (Kindle). White Cloud Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/26/smau-conclusion/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/26/smau-conclusion/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Libya&#39;s Status Today</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Summary of events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2011&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/02/smau-background-libya#oct20&quot;&gt;Gaddafi is killed&lt;/a&gt;. The National Transitional Congress (NTC) announces Libya&#39;s liberation and plans to hold elections within eight months.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2012&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Former rebel forces clash in Benghazi, and Abdel Hafiz Ghoga, the deputy head of the NTC, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-16671590&quot;&gt;resigns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Clashes between rival ethnic groups in the southeast of Libya kill many.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;NTC officials in Benghazi conflict with those in Tripoli.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Government forces struggle to suppress local militias; Tripoli&#39;s airport is temporarily &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/06/04/us-libya-airport-idUSBRE8530H720120604&quot;&gt;commandeered&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Elections are held.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Power is transferred from the TNC to the General National Congress (GNC). Mohammed Magarief is elected to be the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/08/10/us-libya-assembly-idUSBRE8781ID20120810&quot;&gt;interim president&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;September&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Islamist militants &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/2012/09/12/world/africa/libya-consulate-attack-scene/&quot;&gt;attack the American consulate&lt;/a&gt; in Benghazi, leaving a US ambassador and three other Americans dead.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Ali Zeidan replaces Abdul Raheem Al-Keeb as prime minister.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2013&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A law which prohibits Gaddafi-era officials from holding public office is passed. The Chairman of the GNC, Muhammad al-Magarief, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-22693963&quot;&gt;resigns&lt;/a&gt; in compliance.
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Nuri Abu Sahmein is elected as GNC chairman.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Militia forces &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-24051371&quot;&gt;blockade oil export terminals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;An armed militia &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2013/10/10/231321768/libyan-pm-freed-after-gunmen-demand-his-resignation&quot;&gt;abducts Prime Minister Ali Zeidan&lt;/a&gt;, albeit briefly.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The army clashes with armed Islamists in Benghazi, and nine people are killed.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/22/world/africa/libya-blast/&quot;&gt;suicide attack&lt;/a&gt; occurs in Benghazi.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2014&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Protests erupt in response to the GNC&#39;s refusal to step down after their term expired.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Prime Minister Ali Zeidan is removed from office after the Libyan navy fails to stop a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/africa/2014/03/us-navy-seals-board-rouge-libya-oil-tanker-201431710529805169.html&quot;&gt;rogue oil tanker&lt;/a&gt; from escaping. Abdullah al-Thani takes over in Zeidan&#39;s stead. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;April&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Al-Thani negotiates with militia forces to remove blockades for two oil export terminals and, later in the month, submits his resignation. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Ahmed Maiteeq is elected prime minister in al-Thani&#39;s place. Army general Khalifa Haftar defects and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stream.aljazeera.com/story/201405262200-0023759&quot;&gt;launches airstrikes&lt;/a&gt; against militant Islamist groups in Benghazi. Haftar also accuses Prime Minister Maiteeq of being tied to Islamists and attempts to storm the parliament building.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Prime Minister Maiteeq&#39;s appointment is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/10/world/middleeast/libya-court-rejects-disputed-vote-to-replace-interim-prime-minister.html&quot;&gt;deemed illegal&lt;/a&gt;; he resigns. Elections have a low turn out due to security concerns and protests. Conflicts arise between supporters of the outbound GNC and the newly elected parliament.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Militant Islamist groups overtake most of Benghazi. Foreigners flee the country.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;UN reports that hundreds of thousands of people were displaced by civil war. Talks are brokered between rival governments in Tobruk and Tripoli. ISIL &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnn.com/2014/11/18/world/isis-libya/&quot;&gt;takes over the port of Derna&lt;/a&gt; in eastern Libya. The Libyan army regains control of most of Benghazi.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/free-libya.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;free-libya&quot;&gt;
&lt;small&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#damron&quot;&gt;(Damron, 2011)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libyan army and militia forces in Tripoli agreed to a partial ceasefire in January, but Islamist militants continued their violent attacks, killing nine people in an attack on the Corinthia Hotel in Tripoli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February, ISIL released a video of 21 Egyptian Coptic Christians being killed; Egypt bombed ISIL targets within Libya in response. Violence continued to escalate, so the Italian government closed its embassy in Tripoli and withdrew all citizens. The law barring Gaddafi-era officials from public office was also lifted this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late March, the UN released a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2015/04/deaths-reported-fighting-libya-capital-150418074151426.html&quot;&gt;plan&lt;/a&gt; to end the Libyan conflict, proposing the creation of a transitional unity government that would run the country until a new constitution was approved and elections were held.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April thus far has echoed much of the calamity of the previous few months:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thousands of migrants have fled the country&amp;#39;s violence by sea. Italian authorities estimate that over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-32360586&quot;&gt;10,000 migrants&lt;/a&gt; have been picked up within the past several &lt;em&gt;days&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hundreds &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/22/world/europe/italy-libya-migrant-boat-capsize.html&quot;&gt;died tragically&lt;/a&gt; on the route from Libya to Italy just a few days ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ISIL has released video from their base in Libya of the killing of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/apr/19/isis-video-purports-to-show-massacre-of-two-groups-of-ethiopian-christians&quot;&gt;30 Ethiopian Christians&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister of Italy Matteo Renzi spoke of recent tragedies: &amp;quot;I think the Mediterranean is a sea and not a cemetery. The problem at this moment is the situation on the ground in Libya&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#bbc-libya-crisis&quot;&gt;(“Libya crisis: Obama appeals to Gulf states,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/02/smau-background-libya#triggers&quot;&gt;triggers&lt;/a&gt; attributed to the start of Libya&amp;#39;s revolution—volatility, corruption, and repression—have &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/16/smau-sm-today-libya#freedom-house&quot;&gt;remained the same or increased slightly&lt;/a&gt; in the past four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, Zahra Langhi spoke about why Libya&amp;#39;s revolution didn&amp;#39;t work, pointing out that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi left behind a heavy burden, a legacy of tyranny, corruption and seeds of diversions. For four decades Gaddafi&amp;#39;s tyrannical regime destroyed the infrastructure as well as the culture and the moral fabric of Libyan society...Our society, shaped by a revolutionary mindset, became more polarized and has driven away from the ideals and the principles -- freedom, dignity, social justice -- that we first held. Intolerance, exclusion and revenge became the icons of the [aftermath] of the revolution &lt;a href=&quot;#langhi&quot;&gt;(Langhi, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, President Obama is trying to encourage &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-32360586&quot;&gt;Gulf countries&lt;/a&gt; to help with the restoration of stability in Libya. It&amp;#39;s expected that the European Union will also become more involved as they encounter greater numbers of migrants seeking refuge at their borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011 Ed Husain, a senior fellow for Middle Eastern Studies at the Council on Foreign Relations, asserted that &amp;quot;democracy is about much more than removal of dictators and elections&amp;quot; and then noted that &amp;quot;the lack of Arab outcry, for example, about the public manhandling and mobile-phone recording of his [Gaddafi&amp;#39;s] blood-stained corpse by his killers is an indication that yesterday’s rebels are not necessarily prepared to embrace democratic culture&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#husain&quot;&gt;(Husain, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tunisia still experiences challenges but has had the most success establishing a democracy thus far. Egypt is back under severe military rule, though demands for democracy can still be seen and heard. In Libya, the struggle isn&amp;#39;t a clear battle with &amp;quot;the people&amp;quot; on one side and &amp;quot;the regime&amp;quot; on the other; citizens are stuck in the middle of a war between the government and armed militias or armed militias fighting other militias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libya&amp;#39;s diffuse population, isolated from the concept of civil and political institutions for over 40 years, likely plays a part in the unique struggle we&amp;#39;re witnessing. The country&amp;#39;s oil wealth also likely plays a role. When comparing Tunisia, Egypt, and Libya&amp;#39;s current statuses, what stands out most is the fact that the international community only intervened in Libya&amp;#39;s uprisings. Had there been no intervention, it&amp;#39;s possible that rebel forces would have been defeated, and the bloodshed in the country could have been far worse, like in Syria. But even after international intervention, ISIL has taken advantage of the power vacuum and established a foothold in Libya. So perhaps the question of intervention&amp;#39;s role shouldn&amp;#39;t be a binary comparison between intervention and non-intervention, but rather one of the approach and commitment of the intervenors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rory Stewart, a British diplomat and politician said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intervention is far more uncertain than any conceivable domestic policy. You are charging into a dark room, unsure whether there is even a floor beneath your feet. There is no magic plan, nor quantity of resources, that can guarantee success...If there is a lesson from all these countries, it is that there is no substitute for detailed experience in a particular place. The best the west can do is to rely on more people who are focused on the specific history and culture of Libya, more attentive to the realities of rural life &lt;a href=&quot;#stewart&quot;&gt;(Stewart, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Next up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll offer my conclusion on the role of social media in the Arab uprisings. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;the project summary&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;chandler&quot;&gt;Chandler, D. (2015). The R2P Is Dead, Long Live the R2P: The Successful Separation of Military Intervention from the Responsibility to Protect. &lt;i&gt;International Peacekeeping&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;22&lt;/i&gt;(1), 1–5. doi:10.1080/13533312.2014.992572&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bbc-libya-now&quot;&gt;Libya profile - Timeline. (2015, February). BBC. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13755445&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13755445&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;damron&quot;&gt;Damron, S. (2011). &lt;i&gt;free libya graffiti&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sadsnaps/5718768635/in/photolist-9HmbFe-j3gC6e-9moxrU&quot;&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sadsnaps/5718768635/in/photolist-9HmbFe-j3gC6e-9moxrU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bbc-libya-crisis&quot;&gt;Libya crisis: Obama appeals to Gulf states. (2015, April). BBC. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-32360586&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-32360586&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;langhi&quot;&gt;Langhi, Z. (2012, December). Why Libya’s revolution didn’t work — and what might. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/zahra_langhi_why_libya_s_revolution_didn_t_work_and_what_might/transcript?language=en&quot;&gt;https://www.ted.com/talks/zahra_langhi_why_libya_s_revolution_didn_t_work_and_what_might/transcript?language=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;stewart&quot;&gt;Stewart, R. (2011, October). What can Afghanistan and Bosnia teach us about Libya? The Guardian. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/08/libya-intervention-rory-stewart&quot;&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/08/libya-intervention-rory-stewart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;greenemeier&quot;&gt;Greenemeier, L. (2011, October). What Impact Could Gaddafi’s Death Have on Arab Spring Unrest? Scientific American: Observations. Retrieved from &lt;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/2011/10/21/what-impact-could-gaddafis-death-have-on-arab-spring-unrest/ &amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;husain&quot;&gt;Husain, E. (2011). The Real Risks of Chaos. The New York Times: Room for Debate. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/20/qaddafis-end-the-mideasts-future/the-real-risks-of-chaos&quot;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/20/qaddafis-end-the-mideasts-future/the-real-risks-of-chaos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/23/smau-libya-today/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/23/smau-libya-today/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Egypt&#39;s Status Today</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Summary of events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2011&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#feb11&quot;&gt;Mubarak is removed from rule&lt;/a&gt;, and power is assumed by the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces (SCAF).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Constitutional reforms which allow new elections are approved&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;April&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Tahrir Square fills with protestors, demonstrating against the slow pace of political change.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May-July&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Protests for political change continue in Tahrir Square.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The Army removes protestors from Tahrir Square.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Security forces and Coptic Christians clash; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-15235212&quot;&gt;24 people are killed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Protestors return to Tahrir Square and clash with security forces; Prime Minister Essam Sharaf &lt;a href=&quot;http://english.alarabiya.net/articles/2011/11/21/178463.html&quot;&gt;resigns&lt;/a&gt; as a result of continued unrest. The new parliamentary elections begin.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Prime Minister Kama al-Ganzouri takes office.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2012&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Islamist parties win the parliamentary elections.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The state of emergency put in place in 1981 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/egypt/9303195/Egypts-state-of-emergency-ends-after-31-years.html&quot;&gt;ends&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Mohammed Morsi wins the presidential election. Mubarak is sentenced to life in prison.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;New Prime Minister Hisham Qandil appoints a new cabinet, which &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-19075291&quot;&gt;gains criticism&lt;/a&gt; for keeping Mubarak&#39;s old defense minister, Hussein Tantawi, and including only a small number of Christians and women. President Morsi eliminates military say in legislation and drafting of a new constitution.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;President Morsi issues a decree that keeps the judicial branch from questioning his rule but then retracts it when protests erupt.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A draft constitution which emphasizes the role of Islam and restricts freedom of speech and assembly is approved. The Egyptian public approves it, which triggers protests by Christians, women&#39;s and secular groups.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2013&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Violent protests result in over 50 killed; Field Marshal Abdel Fattah el-Sisi warns of a potential state collapse.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;President Morsi attempts to move parliamentary elections forward to April but is stopped by the court. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Islamist allies are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/worldviews/wp/2013/06/18/egypt-appoints-member-of-terror-group-that-once-massacred-tourists-to-run-tourism-region/&quot;&gt;appointed&lt;/a&gt; as regional leaders in half of Egypt&#39;s governorships by Morsi, including one associated with a group that killed tourists in Luxor. Protests and the resignation of Luxor&#39;s governor result.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The SCAF removes Morsi from power, and Adly Mansour is appointed as interim president.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Morsi supporters protesting in Cairo are attacked by security forces. Human Rights Watch reports that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hrw.org/node/128076&quot;&gt;at least 1,150 were killed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;September&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The Muslim Brotherhood is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/24/world/middleeast/egyptian-court-bans-muslim-brotherhood.html&quot;&gt;banned by the courts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A law is passed restricting public protests.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The Egyptian government declares the Muslim Brotherhood a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle_east/egypts-military-backed-government-declares-muslim-brotherhood-a-terrorist-organization/2013/12/25/7cf075ca-6da0-11e3-aecc-85cb037b7236_story.html&quot;&gt;terrorist organization&lt;/a&gt; after a bombing is attributed to them.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2014&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A new constitution is drafted, which bans parties based on religion.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Prime Minister Hazem el-Beblawi and his cabinet &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/25/world/middleeast/egypts-prime-minister-resigns.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;resign abruptly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Abdul Fattah el-Sisi runs for and wins the presidential election.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Three al-Jazeera journalists are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-27943387&quot;&gt;imprisoned&lt;/a&gt; on charges of spreading false news and associating with the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The military is granted additional power and a state of emergency is implemented in Sinai as conflicts with jihadist group Ansar Beit al-Maqdis escalate. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Ansar Beit al-Maqdis &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2014/11/egypt-armed-group-pledges-allegiance-isil-2014111062135628610.html&quot;&gt;announces their loyalty&lt;/a&gt; to the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant (ISIL).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/anti-scaf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;anti-scaf.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;small&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#el-hamalawy&quot;&gt;(el-Hamalawy, 2011)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January, violent protests continued as Egypt&amp;#39;s four year anniversary of the overthrow of the Mubarak regime passed. Continued conflicts with terrorist groups in the Sinai have led the government to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/09/world/middleeast/egypt-moves-to-eradicate-town-near-gaza-strip.html&quot;&gt;raze the city of Rafah&lt;/a&gt; and create a buffer zone along the border shared with the Gaza Strip. In February, Egypt retaliated to ISIL&amp;#39;s execution of 21 Egyptian Coptic Christians by bombing their positions in eastern Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parliamentary elections were set to be held in March but were then &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/03/egyptian-court-suspends-parliamentary-elections-150303130411282.html&quot;&gt;suspended&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;#39;re now expected to be held in May or June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#triggers&quot;&gt;problems&lt;/a&gt; attributed to the start of Egypt&amp;#39;s revolution—corruption, economic disparity, and repression—have &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/14/smau-sm-today-egypt#freedom-house&quot;&gt;remained the same or become more severe&lt;/a&gt; over the past four years. The most significant increase, however, can be seen in the government&amp;#39;s use of military and police force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Repression&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, presidents Mansour and Sisi put over 140 laws into effect that criminalized new behaviors and increased punishments for existing offenses. Egypt&amp;#39;s war against terrorism has further justified the government&amp;#39;s establishment of more draconian laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the military takeover of 2013, a public discourse has evolved churning out incessant accounts in which enemies of the Egyptian state and its people, external and internal, known and unknown, human and otherwise, are constantly conspiring to plot against the country and target its security as well as the health of its national economy. Against a rich tapestry of intrigue and terrorist discourse, the security apparatus has emerged, in this narrative, as the only national saviour capable of protecting the country from complete chaos. In fact, the legitimacy of the Sisi regime continues to derive largely from his promise to rid the country of terrorists and to restore security and order. In this regard, he makes grateful use of actual violent attacks against military and other targets especially in Sinai &lt;a href=&quot;#abdelrahman&quot;&gt;(Abdelrahman, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March of 2014, Alaa Abdel Fattah, founder of the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/14/smau-sm-today-egypt#trials&quot;&gt;No Military Trials for Civilians&lt;/a&gt; movement, was accused of assaulting a police officer and stealing his communication device during a demonstration. Other officers corroborated this testimony against Fattah, though questions have been raised about the legitimacy of this information, due to conflicting statements. Fattah and another political protestor were jailed pending trial, which is permissible under Egypt&amp;#39;s emergency law: &amp;quot;When the prosecution and judiciary know that the case file isn&amp;#39;t powerful enough to guarantee a jail sentence, they keep the defendant in jail pending the trial, which they decide how long is going to take&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#sabry&quot;&gt;(Sabry, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;. Fattah was sentenced to five years in jail in February of 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 11th, U.S. citizen Mohamed Soltan was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2015/04/11/398992763/egyptian-court-sentences-u-s-citizen-to-life-in-prison&quot;&gt;sentenced to life in prison&lt;/a&gt; for alleged ties with the Muslim Brotherhood, and over a dozen others were sentenced to death for their involvement in protests against Morsi&amp;#39;s ouster. Morsi himself was sentenced to 20 years in prison &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/apr/21/egypts-ex-president-mohamed-morsi-jailed-protest-deaths-muslim-brotherhood&quot;&gt;today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. lifted its military supply ban on Egypt at the end of March. As a result, Sisi&amp;#39;s military will be armed with F-16s, missiles, and tanks. Annual military funding of $1.3 billion has also been reinstated &lt;a href=&quot;#calamur&quot;&gt;(Calamur, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maha Abdelrahman, a lecturer at the University of Cambridge, spoke of the broader implications of what&amp;#39;s happening in Egypt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An inflated police force is not unique to Egypt. With the rise of neoliberal capitalism and its strategies of ‘accumulation by dispossession’, many regimes, including those in the ‘democratic’ west, have increased investment in policing and surveillance, especially targeting particular localities and populations; namely the poor, the unemployed, migrants and blacks. Different policies such as the infamous ‘stop and search’, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ipna.co.uk/&quot;&gt;‘Injunctions for the Prevention of Nuisance and Annoyance’&lt;/a&gt; in the UK and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.police.wa.gov.au/Yoursafety/Antisocialbehaviour/tabid/1076/Default.aspx&quot;&gt;‘Prohibited Behaviour Order’&lt;/a&gt; in the State of Western Australia have created a ‘culture of reporting’ and often given increasing discretionary powers to the police &lt;a href=&quot;#abdelrahman&quot;&gt;(Abdelrahman, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summary of scary shit: Heavily militarized police presence in Ferguson. Protests banned. Journalists threatened. News helicopters barred.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Radley Balko (@radleybalko) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/radleybalko/status/499282827738120192&quot;&gt;August 12, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Radley Balko is an American journalist who writes for the Washington Post and published &lt;em&gt;Rise of the Warrior Cop: The Militarization of America’s Police Forces&lt;/em&gt; in 2014. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riots last year in Ferguson, Missouri were met by a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/police-militarization-ferguson-2014-8&quot;&gt;militarized police force&lt;/a&gt;. The Wall Street Journal noted that &amp;quot;billions of dollars of excess military equipment and funding to buy other gear has flown to local police departments over the past two decades&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#grossman&quot;&gt;(Grossman, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attention to cases of police brutality, especially toward minority groups, has increased in the past year. Yesterday, the New York Times released an article, &amp;quot;1.5 Million Black Men,&amp;quot; which found that &amp;quot;Ferguson has 60 men for every 100 black women in the age group,&amp;quot; and that &amp;quot;incarceration and early deaths are the overwhelming drivers of the gap&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#wolfers&quot;&gt;(Wolfers, Leonhardt, &amp;amp; Quealy, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alaa Abdel Fattah&amp;#39;s father spoke at a news conference after his son was first imprisoned: &amp;quot;Is your generation going to pass on to my grandchildren, your children, a better society than that we passed on to you? I hope so; I hope you succeed in what we failed to accomplish. And again, I am sorry. We couldn&amp;#39;t accomplish for you what we had hoped&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#sabry&quot;&gt;(Sabry, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;. The United States and Egypt differ in many distinct ways, but state and federal governments&amp;#39; actions implicate support for the tactics being used toward citizens in Egypt. We too should sincerely ask ourselves if we&amp;#39;re passing a better society on to future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the status and stability of governmental institutions in Libya today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bbc-egypt-now&quot;&gt;Egypt profile - Timeline. (2015). &lt;i&gt;BBC&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13315719&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13315719&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;el-hamalawy&quot;&gt;el-Hamalawy, H. (2011). &lt;i&gt;Anti-SCAF cartoons and graffiti, Tahrir Square ميدان التحرير&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/elhamalawy/6359941401&quot;&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/elhamalawy/6359941401&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hrw-egypt&quot;&gt;All According to Plan: The Rab’a Massacre and Mass Killings of Protesters in Egypt. (2014, August). Human Rights Watch. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hrw.org/reports/2014/08/12/all-according-plan-0&quot;&gt;http://www.hrw.org/reports/2014/08/12/all-according-plan-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abdelrahman&quot;&gt;Abdelrahman, M. (2015, February). Report thy neighbour: policing Sisi’s Egypt. openDemocracy. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/5050/maha-abdelrahman/report-thy-neighbour-policing-sisi%E2%80%99s-egypt&quot;&gt;https://www.opendemocracy.net/5050/maha-abdelrahman/report-thy-neighbour-policing-sisi%E2%80%99s-egypt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;tawfik&quot;&gt;Tawfik Amer, R. (2014, June). The return of tamed opposition in Egypt. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/5050/rawia-m-tawfik-amer/return-of-tamed-opposition-in-egypt&quot;&gt;https://www.opendemocracy.net/5050/rawia-m-tawfik-amer/return-of-tamed-opposition-in-egypt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;calamur&quot;&gt;Calamur, K. (2015, March). Obama Releases Frozen Military Aid To Egypt. NPR: The Two-Way. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2015/03/31/396625135/obama-releases-frozen-military-aid-to-egypt&quot;&gt;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2015/03/31/396625135/obama-releases-frozen-military-aid-to-egypt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kirkpatrick-egypt&quot;&gt;Kirkpatrick, D. D. (2015, March). Egypt Says It May Send Troops to Yemen to Fight Houthis. New York Times. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/27/world/middleeast/saudi-arabia-houthis-yemen.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/27/world/middleeast/saudi-arabia-houthis-yemen.html?_r=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sabry&quot;&gt;Sabry, M. (2014, September). How Egypt’s protest law brought down the revolution. Al Monitor. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2014/09/egypt-protest-law-courts-ruling-abdel-fattah.html#&quot;&gt;http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2014/09/egypt-protest-law-courts-ruling-abdel-fattah.html#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;grossman&quot;&gt;Grossman, A. (2014, September). Senators Criticize Growing Militarization of Local Police Departments. The Wall Street Journal. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/senators-criticize-militarization-of-local-police-departments-1410287125&quot;&gt;http://www.wsj.com/articles/senators-criticize-militarization-of-local-police-departments-1410287125&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wolfers&quot;&gt;Wolfers, J., Leonhardt, D., &amp;amp; Quealy, K. (2015, April). 1.5 Million Missing Black Men. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/04/20/upshot/missing-black-men.html?abt=0002&amp;amp;abg=0&quot;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2015/04/20/upshot/missing-black-men.html?abt=0002&amp;amp;abg=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/21/smau-egypt-today/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/21/smau-egypt-today/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Tunisia&#39;s Status Today</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Summary of events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2011&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/26/smau-background-tunisia#jan14&quot;&gt;Ben Ali is removed from rule&lt;/a&gt;, and an interim national government is established by Prime Minister Mohammed Ghannouchi.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Ghannouchi resigns from his role as Prime Minister.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A court order dissolves Ben Ali&#39;s political party, Rally for Constitutional Democracy (RCD).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Parliamentary elections are held, and the Ennahda Islamist party wins the largest number of votes. Secularist parties agree to an alliance with Ennahda, which cause some citizens to call them traitors.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;November&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The assembly that was elected to draft a new constitution convenes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Moncef Marzouki is elected President, and Hamadi Jebali becomes Prime Minister.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2012&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;June&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;A curfew is imposed by the government after riots increase.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;August&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The draft of the constitution is found to reduce women&#39;s rights, which results in protests in Tunis.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2013&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;February&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Large, violent protests occur after anti-Islamist leader, Chokri Belaid, is killed. Demands for government officials to step down increase. Prime Minister Jebali &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-21508498&quot;&gt;resigns&lt;/a&gt; after his Islamist party, Ennahda, rejects a proposal to form a new coalition government in response to the killing.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Clashes between police and protestors escalate.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;July&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Politician Mohamed Brahmi is assassinated, which results in mass protests, a general strike, and increased demands for the government&#39;s resignation.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The Ennahda party agrees to hand over power to a caretaker government and new elections are scheduled for 2014.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Mehdi Jomaa is appointed Prime Minister of the Tunisian interim government.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;2014&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;January&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Tunisia&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/ar/politics/2014/01/tunisia-arab-spring-back-secular-path.html&quot;&gt;first constitution&lt;/a&gt; is passed and signed by the leaders of the secular-Islamist alliance. It was lauded as a reflection of the diversity of Tunisian society and reflective of its pluralism. An interim cabinet is appointed to govern until the new elections are held.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;March&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;President Marzouki removes the national state of emergency.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;May&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Electoral laws are established to govern the legislative and presidential elections.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;October&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;The Nidaa Tounes party—comprised of secularists and some former party members of Ben Ali&#39;s regime—overtakes the Islamist Ennahda party, winning the largest number of seats in the parliamentary election.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;December&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Beji Caid Essebsi of the Nidaa Tounes party is elected President.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lutte-finale.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lutte finale&quot;&gt;
&lt;small&gt; &amp;quot;This is the final struggle&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#bocquet&quot;&gt;(Bocquet, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tunisia is considered to be the Arab uprisings&amp;#39; greatest success story. This has has been attributed to some common factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The interim government focused first on creating a constitution that established human rights as law and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; held elections for a permanent government &lt;a href=&quot;#levine&quot;&gt;(LeVine, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tunisia didn&amp;#39;t get the international attention or pressure that other countries like Libya and Egypt did, so their transition was more natural &lt;a href=&quot;#ryan&quot;&gt;(Ryan, 2014, p. 20)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Election results were not interfered with as they were in Egypt; Tunisia&amp;#39;s Islamic government was not removed by the military &lt;a href=&quot;#mclarney&quot;&gt;(McLarney, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tunisia is relatively small geographically, and the majority of the population have the same ethnic and religious backgrounds &lt;a href=&quot;#keating&quot;&gt;(Keating, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country held its second round of democratic elections at the end of 2014. Secularist party Nidaa Tounes assumed majority control over parliament and formed a coalition government with Islamist party, Ennahda, in early 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;#mclarney&quot;&gt;(McLarney, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ongoing issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/26/smau-background-tunisia#triggers&quot;&gt;triggers&lt;/a&gt; attributed to the start of the revolution, repression and censorship have &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/12/smau-sm-today-tunisia#freedom-house&quot;&gt;decreased most significantly&lt;/a&gt;. Economic disparity and concerns about corruption are still ongoing issues within the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Corruption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns have been expressed about the election of Essebsi, a remnant of the Bourguiba and Ben Ali eras, and a party which includes several prominent old regime players from the RCD. Teyeb and Levine accused the transitional government of failing to prosecute politicians who worked with or within the Ben Ali regime. As a result, RCD supporters have continued to influence the political, economic, and social realms, contributing to an increase in corruption post-revolution &lt;a href=&quot;#teyeb&quot;&gt;(Teyeb, 2014; LeVine, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teyeb warns that the &amp;quot;RCD machine&amp;quot; is &amp;quot;implanted in all the components of the State, from public services to education, health sector, business and the media&amp;quot; and that &amp;quot;any setback for Tunisia’s recent democratic achievements will mean a threat to freedom of the press, to transparency and good governance, to political plurality&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#teyeb&quot;&gt;(Teyeb, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Economic disparity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tunisian interim government&amp;#39;s decision to focus first on creating a constitution and a stable political institution has left the economy in a state of neglect: &amp;quot;Today, excitement over the constitution is tempered by economic hardship. Newly acquired political freedoms are widely perceived as having come at the price of economic stability and security&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#ryan&quot;&gt;(Ryan, 2014, p. 21)&lt;/a&gt;. And economic stability plays a hand in the security of the country, as Levine asserts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same dynamics of unemployment, marginalisation and lack of a future that helped radicalise the killers of Paris, is also quite present in Tunisia, which accounts for the rapid rise of extremism under the democratic transition, including the disproportionately large participation of young Tunisians in jihadist activities in Iraq and Syria &lt;a href=&quot;#levine&quot;&gt;(LeVine, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremist groups like ISIL are also threats to internal security. This was underscored in March 2015 when &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.bbc.com/news/world-africa-31941672&quot;&gt;terrorists attacked tourists&lt;/a&gt; at the Bardo museum in Tunis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tunisia&amp;#39;s ambassador to the US, Mohamed Chelaifa acknowledged the need to address socio-economic inequalities, saying &amp;quot;it was Tunisia&amp;#39;s high unemployment and poor economic conditions that sparked the uprising&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#hanley&quot;&gt;(Hanley, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parallels can be drawn between Tunisia&amp;#39;s struggles and those we have in the United States:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have extremists, and sometimes they &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/06/us/shooting-reported-at-temple-in-wisconsin.html&quot;&gt;kill people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CEOs make up to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/kathryndill/2014/04/15/report-ceos-earn-331-times-as-much-as-average-workers-774-times-as-much-as-minimum-wage-earners/&quot;&gt;774 times&lt;/a&gt; as much as minimum wage workers who are protesting for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/apr/15/fight-for-15-minimum-wage-protests-new-york-los-angeles-atlanta-boston&quot;&gt;$15 an hour&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The uneducated, the disaffected, and the desperate are targets for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fbi.gov/stats-services/publications/2011-national-gang-threat-assessment&quot;&gt;recruitment by gangs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;#39;ve experienced &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2015/jan/7/gridlock-in-congress-rekindled-quickly-despite-dem/?page=all&quot;&gt;gridlock in Congress&lt;/a&gt; and we&amp;#39;ve seen and heard demands for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teaparty.org/impeach-obama-petition/&quot;&gt;removal of leaders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerns about corruption and economic disparity are valid but should not undermine the significance of the accomplishments Tunisia has made. If Tunisia&amp;#39;s new leaders find ways to earnestly engage the youth who first called for revolution, it is far more likely that these complex issues can be effectively addressed. Engaging the disenfranchised—giving them a sense of purpose and hope—could also help delegitimize extremist factions looking for recruits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the status and stability of governmental institutions in Egypt today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bocquet&quot;&gt;Bocquet, D. (2012). &lt;i&gt;&amp;quot;C’est la lutte finale&amp;quot; Tunis Médina, January 2012&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/66944824@N05/6795398487/in/photostream/&quot;&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/66944824@N05/6795398487/in/photostream/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bbc-tunisia-now&quot;&gt;Tunisia profile - Timeline. (2015). &lt;i&gt;BBC&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-14107720&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-14107720&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hanley&quot;&gt;Hanley, D. C. (2014). Tunisia: The Way Forward. &lt;i&gt;The Washington Report on Middle East Affairs&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;33&lt;/i&gt;(3), 62. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://login.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/login?url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/1526143084?accountid=4485&quot;&gt;http://login.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/login?url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/1526143084?accountid=4485&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;cavatorta&quot;&gt;Haugbølle, R. H., &amp;amp; Cavatorta, F. (2012). Beyond Ghannouchi. &lt;i&gt;Middle East Research and Information Project&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;42&lt;/i&gt;(262). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.merip.org.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/mer/mer262/beyond-ghannouchi&quot;&gt;http://www.merip.org.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/mer/mer262/beyond-ghannouchi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ryan&quot;&gt;Ryan, Y. (2014). Tunisia’s Passage. &lt;i&gt;The Nation&lt;/i&gt;, 19–21.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levine&quot;&gt;LeVine, M. (2015, January). Tunisia still on the brink. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2015/01/tunisia-still-brink-2015113113441123913.html&quot;&gt;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2015/01/tunisia-still-brink-2015113113441123913.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mclarney&quot;&gt;McLarney, E. (2015, February). Why Arab Spring made life better in Tunisia, failed everywhere else. reuters. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.reuters.com/great-debate/2015/02/18/why-arab-spring-made-life-better-in-tunisia-failed-everywhere-else/&quot;&gt;http://blogs.reuters.com/great-debate/2015/02/18/why-arab-spring-made-life-better-in-tunisia-failed-everywhere-else/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;teyeb&quot;&gt;Teyeb, M. (2014). Tunisia: Political comeback of Ben Ali’s cohort a setback to democracy. &lt;i&gt;African Arguments&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://africanarguments.org/2014/11/18/tunisia-political-comeback-of-ben-alis-cohort-a-setback-to-democracy-by-mourad-tayeb/&quot;&gt;http://africanarguments.org/2014/11/18/tunisia-political-comeback-of-ben-alis-cohort-a-setback-to-democracy-by-mourad-tayeb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;keating&quot;&gt;Keating, J. (2015, January). Why Was Tunisia the Only Arab Spring Country That Turned Out Well? slate. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2015/01/28/why_was_tunisia_the_only_arab_spring_country_that_turned_out_well.html&quot;&gt;http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2015/01/28/why_was_tunisia_the_only_arab_spring_country_that_turned_out_well.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wb-tunisia&quot;&gt;World Bank Report: Young People in Tunisia Still Frustrated by Social and Economic Obstacles. (2014, October). World Bank. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2014/10/02/world-bank-report-young-people-tunisia-frustrated-social-economic-obstacles&quot;&gt;http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2014/10/02/world-bank-report-young-people-tunisia-frustrated-social-economic-obstacles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;marcusa&quot;&gt;Marcusa, M. (2014). Potholes in the Road to Revolution. Middle East Research and Information Project. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.merip.org.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/mer/mer272/potholes-road-revolution&quot;&gt;http://www.merip.org.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/mer/mer272/potholes-road-revolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/19/smau-tunisia-today/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/19/smau-tunisia-today/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Social Media in Libya Today</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Libya has struggled to achieve peace and stability. After Gaddafi&#39;s death, the country broke into factions based on tribes, regions, and even cities. In July of 2012, Libya&#39;s first parliamentary elections were held and the National Transitional Congress (NTC) handed power over to the General National Congress (GNC). Sectarian attacks continued, and an Islamist militant attack on the American consulate in Benghazi in September 2012 resulted in the death of a U.S. ambassador and three other people. In October 2012, the Libyan Prime Minister was ousted. His successor was removed by March 2013 and replaced by the current Prime Minister, Abdullah al-Thani.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In June 2014, elections were held to fill the Council of Deputies—the organization that was to replace the GNC—but when secularists and liberals did well, Islamist lawmakers rejected the results of the elections and refused to recognize the Council of Deputies. Islamists and their supporters established a New General National Congress in Tripoli, and those elected to the Council of Deputies fled to Tobruk. The country has been in a state of civil war since then, which has left room for militant groups such as the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant (ISIL) to take advantage of uncontrolled areas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Social media use has steadily increased in Libya as it has in Tunisia and Egypt. We&#39;ll look at statistics from the Arab Social Media Report, the UN, the International Telecommunication Union (ITU), and the Freedom House in order to assess its role in Libya today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Libya has the lowest rate of Facebook use of the three countries studied for this project. For Libyans ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Facebook on February 16, 2011 was at 4.21%. In May 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 13.5%, or 878,400 people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=z2kg90qa3mgc2e_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=facebookpenetration&amp;amp;fdim_y=age_group:13%26above&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:LY:EG&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1367384400000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 2013, Facebook was the most visited site in Libya. It has served as a source of news for Libyans. Many city and government officials used it to share updates and communications with their constituents. Citizens used it for political campaigns like the “No Extension of GNC” movement, which protested the GNC retaining power after its transitional deadline had passed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Libya has the lowest rate of Twitter use of the three countries studied for this project. For Libyans ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Twitter on September 1, 2011 was at 0.07% &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In March 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 0.22%; by March of 2014, the rate of use was at 0.67%, or 44,100 people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=inka2ndrsatap_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=TwitterPenetration&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:EG:LY&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1362117600000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Like Facebook, Twitter has also been used in political and civic campaigns. Recently, Tunisians bombarded US ambassador Deborah Jones with criticism after she tweeted about unconfirmed deaths in an air strike:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Terrible news today from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Tarhouna?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Tarhouna&lt;/a&gt; where 8 innocent displaced &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Tawergha?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Tawergha&lt;/a&gt; killed in air strikes. This violence serves no one&amp;#39;s interests.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Safira Deborah (@SafiraDeborah) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SafiraDeborah/status/579974376776429568&quot;&gt;March 23, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Jones shut down her Twitter account due to the onslaught resulting from this post &lt;a href=&quot;#stephen&quot;&gt;(Stephen, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Internet and Mobile Access Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Libya&#39;s rates of Internet access are the lowest of the three countries in this project. The damage of war can be attributed to much of the country&#39;s struggle to provide and maintain information and communications technology (ICT) since 2011. Multiple Internet blackouts have occurred due to vandalism and technical failures. The Facebook page “I hate Libyan Telecom and Technology,” was created to protest Libya&#39;s unreliable telecommunications services. It gained over 20,000 followers &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Common points of access to the Internet include homes, workplaces, mobile phones, and hotel lobbies. Cybercafés were severely damaged during the war but are reportedly beginning to make a comeback. The majority of Internet users gain access through wireless WiMax service. Broadband subscriptions are very low, at a rate of just over 1 subscription per 100 residents &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. Two-way satellite Internet technology has also been used by both foreign and Libyan organizations such as Al Jazeera and &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/10/smau-analyses-libya#journalists&quot;&gt;Libya Alhurra&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;small&gt;
    &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Table 1.&lt;/b&gt; UN/International Telecommunication Union Data
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2005&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2010&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Internet use&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (% population)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3.9 &lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;(estimated)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14.0 &lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;(estimated)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14.0 &lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;(estimated)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;16.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Mobile subscriptions&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (# per 100 inhabitants)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;34.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;180.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;163.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;155.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;165.0&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;

&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-internet&quot;&gt;(“Percentage of individuals using the Internet,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-mobile&quot;&gt;(“Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Libya&#39;s mobile phone ratio is the highest of the three countries reviewed for this project. Their heavy use for posting messages, photos, and videos during the 2011 uprisings illustrates their ubiquity. The price of mobile phone subscriptions in Libya dropped when competition was allowed into the country in 2003, which made the technology more accessible to Libyans. Freedom House notes that &quot;smartphones and 3G connectivity have been available since 2006, though the prohibitive cost of compatible handsets impedes their wider dissemination&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Internet Freedom&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;freedom-house&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The categories that Freedom House uses to determine how free a country&#39;s access to the Internet is were defined in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/12/smau-sm-today-tunisia#freedom-house&quot;&gt;Sunday&#39;s post&lt;/a&gt;. The scores from these three categories are added to get a &lt;b&gt;Freedom on the Net Total&lt;/b&gt;, which determines the status level of the country&#39;s Internet freedom—from &lt;i&gt;Free&lt;/i&gt;, like Canada, to &lt;i&gt;Not Free&lt;/i&gt;, like China. Libya&#39;s 2014 rating places it solidly in the &lt;i&gt;Partly Free&lt;/i&gt; status.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;
  &lt;small&gt;
  &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Table 2.&lt;/b&gt; Freedom on the Net &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2014&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Obstacles to access &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 25 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;n/a&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Limits on content &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 35 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;n/a&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Violations of user rights &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 40 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;n/a&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Freedom total &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 100 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;n/a&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Freedom status&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;n/a&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When it comes to social media, what&#39;s most striking in Libya is the lack of government censorship. Common tools such as YouTube, Facebook, and Twitter are accessible. Freedom House even noted that &quot;the &#39;Innocence of Muslims&#39; film that sparked protests outside the American consulate in Benghazi was not blocked by Libyan authorities, although it was made inaccessible by YouTube’s parent company, Google&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The greatest threat to free speech in Libya is the threat of violence by militant groups. Activists and journalists receive online threats and have been actively targeted for assassination &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-libya&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Libya,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Utterly devastated &amp;amp; heartbroken...cried myself to sleep Yday..Lost all hope in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Libya?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Libya&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/RIP?src=hash&quot;&gt;#RIP&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TBensaud&quot;&gt;@TBensaud&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sami_Elkawafi&quot;&gt;@sami_Elkawafi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/N0U948l8aV&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/N0U948l8aV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ahmed Sanalla (@ASanalla) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ASanalla/status/513293903488090112&quot;&gt;September 20, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Youth activist and blogger Tawfik Bensaud was assassinated on September 19, 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;#masi&quot;&gt;(Masi, 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many Libyans self-censor their posts online because of threats of violent retaliation and a long history of oppression under Gaddafi, but a growing number of activists and political bloggers have also emerged despite the risks.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Social media has also been used to combat social issues, like students being unable to attend school due to the violence surrounding them. Haifa El-Zahawi used social media and Skype to spread the word about her project, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.benghazischool.com/&quot;&gt;The Benghazi School&lt;/a&gt;, which offered classes to students through an online portal. Students and teachers hold live classes when they can, but sessions are also recorded and posted online for asynchronous access due to unreliable Internet connectivity. El-Zahawi expressed hope that improved access to education will help deter the radicalization of youth toward groups such as ISIL &lt;a href=&quot;#pri&quot;&gt;(International, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The collapse of Gaddafi&#39;s regime resulted in a socio-political vacuum, which many different groups are now fighting to assume control over &lt;a href=&quot;#el-kasm&quot;&gt;(El Kasm, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. Acemoglu and Robinson spoke at great lengths about the struggle to break out of a vicious cycle of extractive institutions—systems that enrich the lives of a few at the expense of many. In their book, they seem to directly address the MENA region&#39;s–but particularly Libya&#39;s–current struggle, saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A free media and new communication technologies can help only at the margins, by providing information and coordinating the demands and actions of those vying for more inclusive institutions. Their help will translate into meaningful change only when a broad segment of society mobilizes and organizes in order to effect political change, and does so not for sectarian reasons or to take control of extractive institutions, but to transform extractive institutions into more inclusive ones &lt;a href=&quot;#acemoglu&quot;&gt;(Acemoglu &amp;amp; Robinson, 2013, p. 462)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Zahra Langhi spoke of Libya&#39;s failures in its revolution, acknowledging that Libyans needed &quot;national dialogue and consensus-building more than it needed the elections, which only reinforced polarization and division,&quot; and then prescribed &quot;we need to stop acting as agents of rage and calling for days of rage. We need to start acting as agents of compassion and mercy&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#langhi&quot;&gt;(Langhi, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;. Olivos and PaPaioannou reviewed the trends of discussions on three Libyan Facebook pages over the course of three months in 2012 and identified these themes in discussions: Human Rights, Local Themes of Interest within the Libyan Society, the Role of Digital Technologies and Social Mobilization &lt;a href=&quot;#olivos&quot;&gt;(PaPaioannou &amp;amp; Olivos, 2013, p. 105)&lt;/a&gt;. This could be interpreted as promising if the researchers&#39; findings are indicative of a broader shift toward a structure that promotes political inclusion, compassion, and mercy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Next up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the status and stability of governmental institutions in Tunisia today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr&quot;&gt;Arab Social Media Report. (2015). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;freedom-libya&quot;&gt;Freedom House | Libya. (2015). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedomhouse.org/country/libya#.VSmFSBPF-Uc&quot;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/country/libya#.VSmFSBPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-internet&quot;&gt;Percentage of individuals using the Internet. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr14&quot;&gt;Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media. (2014, June). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;pri&quot;&gt;International, P. R. (2015). Libyan Kids Have Been Out of School for Months, so One Woman Is Bringing the Classroom to Them. &lt;i&gt;GlobalVoices&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/02/28/benghazi-skype-school-libya-haifa-el-zahawi/&quot;&gt;http://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/02/28/benghazi-skype-school-libya-haifa-el-zahawi/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;el-kasm&quot;&gt;El Kasm, S. (2011). &lt;i&gt;Rebuilding Libya&lt;/i&gt; (p. 1). Inter-Hemispheric Resource Center Press. Retrieved from http://login.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/login?url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/909052797?accountid=4485&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;olivos&quot;&gt;PaPaioannou, T., &amp;amp; Olivos, H. E. (2013). Cultural identity and social media in the arab spring: Collective goals in the use of Facebook in the libyan context. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Arab &amp;Amp; Muslim Media Research&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;6&lt;/i&gt;(2 &amp;amp; 3), 99–114. Retrieved from &lt;10.1386/jammr.6.2-3.99_1&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;stephen&quot;&gt;Stephen, C. (2015). US ambassador to Libya harassed off Twitter after unverified air strike post. &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/mar/24/libya-us-ambassador-twitter-air-strike-post&quot;&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/mar/24/libya-us-ambassador-twitter-air-strike-post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;masi&quot;&gt;Masi, A. (2014). Benghazi &amp;quot;Black Friday&amp;quot;: Assassinations Targeting Youth Activists And Military Kill 10 In Libya. &lt;i&gt;International Business Times&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ibtimes.com/benghazi-black-friday-assassinations-targeting-youth-activists-military-kill-10-libya-1692424&quot;&gt;http://www.ibtimes.com/benghazi-black-friday-assassinations-targeting-youth-activists-military-kill-10-libya-1692424&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;pri&quot;&gt;International, P. R. (2015). Libyan Kids Have Been Out of School for Months, so One Woman Is Bringing the Classroom to Them. &lt;i&gt;GlobalVoices&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/02/28/benghazi-skype-school-libya-haifa-el-zahawi/&quot;&gt;http://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/02/28/benghazi-skype-school-libya-haifa-el-zahawi/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;acemoglu&quot;&gt;Acemoglu, D., &amp;amp; Robinson, J. (2013). &lt;i&gt;Why Nations Fail: The Origins of Power, Prosperity, and Poverty&lt;/i&gt;. Crown Business.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;langhi&quot;&gt;Langhi, Z. (2012, December). Why Libya’s revolution didn’t work — and what might. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/zahra_langhi_why_libya_s_revolution_didn_t_work_and_what_might/transcript?language=en&quot;&gt;https://www.ted.com/talks/zahra_langhi_why_libya_s_revolution_didn_t_work_and_what_might/transcript?language=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/16/smau-sm-today-libya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/16/smau-sm-today-libya/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Social Media in Egypt Today</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since Mubarak&#39;s removal, Egyptians have struggled to find a leader supportive of their initial cause. Mohamed Morsi was elected in June of 2012 and was removed by Field Marshal Abdel Fattah el-Sisi in July 2013. Adly Mahmoud Mansour served as interim president until elections in May of 2014 announced that el-Sisi had won the presidency with 96% of votes. Protests and violence accompanied the political turmoil.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Despite—or as a result of—the tumultuous state of the country over the past four years, social media use has steadily increased. We&#39;ll look at statistics from the Arab Social Media Report on social media use in the region as well as data from the UN, the International Telecommunication Union (ITU), and the Freedom House in order to assess the state of social media in Egypt today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Egypt has the second highest rate of use (per capita) of the three countries studied for this project. For Egyptians ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Facebook on January 25, 2011 was at 5.9% &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In May 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 16.2%; by May of 2014, the rate of use was at 22.4%, or 19.4 million people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=z2kg90qa3mgc2e_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=facebookpenetration&amp;amp;fdim_y=age_group:13%26above&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:LY:EG&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1367384400000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of 2013, Facebook was the most visited website in Egypt. As the mainstream media reverted back to a self-censored, pro-military stance, citizens more heavily relied upon the site to organize and disseminate their messages. In retaliation, pro-government groups have employed tactics such as reporting pages for violations of Facebook&#39;s terms of service in order to have them shut down. Employers have been used to apply pressure to employees who are vocal on social media, and arrests for associations with anti-regime Facebook pages have taken place on repeated occasions. Some organizations, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#april6&quot;&gt;April 6th Movement&lt;/a&gt;, have even been banned &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;trials&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In spite of efforts to discourage them, many civil and activist organizations have successfully utilized social media for their causes. &lt;i&gt;Kefaya&lt;/i&gt;, or &quot;The Egyptian Movement for Change&quot; and &lt;i&gt;Shayfenkom&lt;/i&gt;, or &quot;We Can See You,&quot; are examples of online campaigns for political movements, and the &quot;No Military Trials for Civilians&quot; page was used to encourage participation in street protests against unjust treatment by the government. Women&#39;s rights campaigns have also had success in raising awareness for their causes through campaign sites such as HarassMap and NooNeswa &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Egypt has the highest rate of Twitter use of the three countries studied for this project. For Egyptians ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Twitter on September 1, 2011 was at 0.15% &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In March 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 0.61%; by March of 2014, the rate of use was at 1.26%, or 1.09 million people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;. Egypt&#39;s use of Twitter has contributed significantly to the fact that Arabic is the fastest growing language on the platform &lt;a href=&quot;#hamdan&quot;&gt;(Hamdan, 2013)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=inka2ndrsatap_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=TwitterPenetration&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:EG:LY&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1362117600000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When el-Sisi issued an ultimatum to Morsi in 2013, Morsi posted his rejection of it on Twitter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%B1%D8%A6%D9%8A%D8%B3?src=hash&quot;&gt;#الرئيس&lt;/a&gt; محمد مرسي يؤكد تمسكه بالشرعية الدستورية ويرفض أي محاولة للخروج عليها ويدعوالقوات المسلحة سحب إنذارها ويرفض أي إملاءات داخليةأوخارجية&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; د.محمد مرسي (@MuhammadMorsi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MuhammadMorsi/status/352164641352327168&quot;&gt;July 2, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Translation: President Mohamed Morsi asserts his grasp on constitutional legitimacy and rejects any attempt to deviate from it, and calls on the armed forces to withdraw their warning and refuses to be dictated to internally or externally &lt;a href=&quot;#fitzpatrick&quot;&gt;(Fitzpatrick, 2013)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, when el-Sisi announced that he would run for the presidency in 2014, opponents and supporters alike took to Twitter to voice their opinions. A blogger explained that Twitter was &quot;the only arena where [Sisi critics] can express their opposition&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Internet and Mobile Access Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Like Tunisia, Egypt&#39;s rates of access to the Internet and mobile phones have steadily increased over the past several years. This has occurred despite a weak telecommunications infrastructure in rural and impoverished areas of the country.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Internet access is less expensive than in some of Egypt&#39;s neighboring countries, but costs are still prohibitively high because a state-owned provider holds the majority of resources. Some areas of the country are not connected to the landline grid, so they cannot access broadband services at all. Many access the internet at cafés, but Egyptians are required to provide their &quot;names, email addresses, and mobile numbers to receive a personal identification number (PIN) to access the internet&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Because of these infrastructural, political, and economic barriers, the Egyptian government does not need to actively censor Internet transmissions. Also, as learned with the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#shutdown&quot;&gt;Internet shutdown&lt;/a&gt; on January 27, 2011 and other blackouts which occurred after that event, &quot;the Egyptian government has centralized internet infrastructure and fiber-optic cables into highly controllable &#39;chokepoints&#39;&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;small&gt;
    &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Table 1.&lt;/b&gt; UN/International Telecommunication Union Data
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2005&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2010&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Internet use&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (% population)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;31.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;39.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;44.1 &lt;i&gt;&lt;small&gt;(estimated)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;49.6&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Mobile subscriptions&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (# per 100 inhabitants)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;18.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;90.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;105.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;119.9&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;121.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;

&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-internet&quot;&gt;(“Percentage of individuals using the Internet,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-mobile&quot;&gt;(“Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mobile phones have grown to exceed a 1:1 ratio. Phone applications like Viber, WhatsApp, Blackberry Messenger, and other Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP) are popular means of communication, though the government explicitly prohibits placing international calls from mobile 3G networks. In June 2014, a leaked document revealed the Egyptian Ministry of Interior planned to buy technology to &quot;conduct real-time monitoring of social media and communication apps such Facebook, Twitter, Viber, and WhatsApp&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Internet Freedom&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;freedom-house&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The categories that Freedom House uses to determine how free a country&#39;s access to the Internet is were defined in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/12/smau-sm-today-tunisia#freedom-house&quot;&gt;Sunday&#39;s post&lt;/a&gt;. The scores from these three categories are added to get a &lt;b&gt;Freedom on the Net Total&lt;/b&gt;, which determines the status level of the country&#39;s Internet freedom—from &lt;i&gt;Free&lt;/i&gt;, like Canada, to &lt;i&gt;Not Free&lt;/i&gt;, like China. With a score of 60, Egypt is right on the cusp of being categorized as &lt;i&gt;Not Free&lt;/i&gt;, the category for countries scoring between 61 and 100 on Freedom House&#39;s scale.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;small&gt;
    &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Table 2.&lt;/b&gt; Freedom on the Net &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2014&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Obstacles to access &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 25 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Limits on content &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 35 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Violations of user rights &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 40 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Freedom total &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0 = best, 100 = worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;54&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Freedom status&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;censor&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In contrast to Tunisia, obstacles to access and violations of user rights have increased since the Arab uprisings in 2011. Limits on content have gone down, but self-censorship has increased. Freedom House explains that this is because the &quot;country’s highly divisive political environment has resulted in increasing verbal harassment between social media users and a declining willingness to speak out on contentious issues, resulting in self-censorship&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Civilians have been subjected to military trials based on comments or media they have posted online, and seven year sentences have been issued for protesting in the streets. Violence and torture of citizens and journalists is still prevalent. In March of 2014, journalist Mayada Ashraf was killed by a sniper while covering a protest. However, Freedom House still reports that &quot;Egyptians remain adept at utilizing social media as an instrument for positive change&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Egypt,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt&amp;#39;s story seemed the most promising and is now one of the most sobering situations in the MENA region since the Arab uprisings first began in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It tells a story of battles won over the influence of Egypt&amp;#39;s mainstream media:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptians recognise that ‘older media’, such as television and radio, though accessed by most, tend to be biased. Still State TV, run by the ruling military, remains most popular, and domestic corporate media channels are self-serving and volatile in their coverage. Yet activists have explained to me that they can influence some of these media from the ‘outside in’ by documenting videos of protests, creating credible blogs, and tweeting stories to influence both international and domestic journalists. I saw these strategies in action in July, 2012 at a recent 23000+ person sit-in in Mahalla, the birthplace of Egypt’s labour movement. While this protest was sparsely reported on by the mainstream media, I observed how activists were using video cameras, blogs, and Facebook/Twitter connections to force this coverage from the outside-in &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan-egypt&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It illustrates how social media technologies can and will be used by both sides of a struggle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were the kings of social media, and now our enemies are catching up with us.” With these words, Ahmed Maher, 2011 revolutionary hero and co-founder of the April 6th Youth Movement, explained to me that today’s battle for political power has two-fronts &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan-egypt&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, like it or not, this technology—or something derivative of it—is here to stay:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 70+ year old military generals’ use of Facebook to release announcement, to the Muslim Brotherhood’s use of hackers, leaders from the entire range of Egypt’s political factions are striving for the upper hand in this fight &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan-egypt&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, however, is the message that &amp;quot;We will watch, listen, and if we do not like what we see - we will rise again&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan-egypt&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the role of social media in Libya today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr&quot;&gt;Arab Social Media Report. (2015). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;freedom-egypt&quot;&gt;Freedom House | Egypt. (2015). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedomhouse.org/country/egypt#.VSmFPRPF-Uc&quot;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/country/egypt#.VSmFPRPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-internet&quot;&gt;Percentage of individuals using the Internet. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr14&quot;&gt;Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media. (2014, June). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;egypt-profile&quot;&gt;Egypt profile - Timeline. (2015). &lt;i&gt;CNN&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;volume&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13315719&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-13315719&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;freedom&quot;&gt;Freedom on the Net. (2015). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedomhouse.org/report-types/freedom-net#.VSnbPhPF-Uc&quot;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/report-types/freedom-net#.VSnbPhPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hamdan&quot;&gt;Hamdan, S. (2013). After Arab Spring, a shift in ads; Companies in Mideast and North Africa follow rising use of social media. &lt;i&gt;The International Herald Tribune&lt;/i&gt;, 14.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;srinivasan-egypt&quot;&gt;Srinivasan, R. (2012). Taking power through technology in the Arab Spring. &lt;i&gt;Al Jazeera&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2012/09/2012919115344299848.html&quot;&gt;http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2012/09/2012919115344299848.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;fitzpatrick&quot;&gt;Fitzpatrick, A. (2013). Morsi Ousted While Sparring With Egyptian Army on Social Media. &lt;i&gt;Mashable&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://mashable.com/2013/07/03/egypt-social-media/&quot;&gt;http://mashable.com/2013/07/03/egypt-social-media/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/14/smau-sm-today-egypt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/14/smau-sm-today-egypt/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Social Media in Tunisia Today</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
The Arab Social Media Report, issued by the Dubai School of Government, speaks favorably of social media&#39;s current role in the region, noting that it is &quot;already providing the medium for overcoming many of the monumental barriers for re-inventing public service in the Arab world&quot; and that &quot;we are also witnessing a new wave of convergence, with online social media tools merging with smart phone messaging applications&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014, pp. 3-4)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We&#39;ll look at these statistics for social media use in the region as well as data from the UN, the International Telecommunication Union (ITU), and the Freedom House in order to assess the state of social media in Tunisia today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tunisia has the highest rate of Facebook use of the three countries studied for this project. For Tunisians ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Facebook on January 13, 2011 was at 18.33% &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In May 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 33.94%; by May of 2014, use was up to 42.1%, or 4.6 million people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;http://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=z2kg90qa3mgc2e_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=facebookpenetration&amp;amp;fdim_y=age_group:13%26above&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:LY:EG&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1367384400000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Facebook is an especially common resource for building and maintaining civic and activist communities. The government has arrested people based on their Facebook activity in the past, but there have been no recorded instances of politically-motivated censorship in the past year &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Tunisia,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tunisia has the second highest rate of Twitter use of the three countries studied for this project. For Tunisians ages 13 and above, the rate of use of Twitter on September 1, 2011 was at 0.09% &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr&quot;&gt;(“Arab Social Media Report,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In March 2013 (see below), this rate had increased to 0.31%; by March of 2014, the rate of use was at 0.34%, or 37,100 people &lt;a href=&quot;#asmr14&quot;&gt;(“Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media,” 2014)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;325&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://www.google.com/publicdata/embed?ds=inka2ndrsatap_&amp;amp;ctype=c&amp;amp;strail=false&amp;amp;bcs=d&amp;amp;nselm=s&amp;amp;met_y=TwitterPenetration&amp;amp;scale_y=lin&amp;amp;ind_y=false&amp;amp;idim=country:TN:EG:LY&amp;amp;ifdim=country&amp;amp;tunit=D&amp;amp;pit=1362117600000&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;dl=en_US&amp;amp;ind=false&amp;amp;icfg&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Youth and civil organizations have used Twitter to live-tweet sessions of the National Constituent Assembly &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Tunisia,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. In March 2015, Tunisians took to Twitter to criticize inaccurate reports that ISIS had taken over the town of Tataouine, whose name inspired the Star Wars fictional planet &lt;a href=&quot;#abrougui&quot;&gt;(Abrougui, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;. Though the topic was serious, many used humor to convey their message:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voici l&amp;#39;émir de Tataouine, un barbu comme vous le voyez &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/JQX11TKrPm&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/JQX11TKrPm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Hédi (@ayalez_hdi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ayalez_hdi/status/580854691761950721&quot;&gt;March 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Translation: &amp;quot;Here is the emir of Tataouine, a bearded man as you see.&amp;quot;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Internet and Mobile Access Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/26/smau-background-tunisia#tech&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, it was noted that Tunisia had one of the highest rates of Internet and mobile phone access in the region. This was thought to have contributed to the success of Tunisia&#39;s uprisings. In the table below, it can be seen that, with the exception of a dip in 2013 mobile rates, Internet use and mobile subscriptions have continued to increase year after year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;small&gt;
    &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Table 1.&lt;/b&gt; UN/International Telecommunication Union Data
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2005&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2010&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Internet use&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (% population)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;9.7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;36.8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;39.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;41.4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;43.8&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Mobile subscriptions&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;br /&gt; (# per 100 inhabitants)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;57.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;104.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;115.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;118.1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;115.6&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-internet&quot;&gt;(“Percentage of individuals using the Internet,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#un-mobile&quot;&gt;(“Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mobile phone subscriptions have grown to exceed a 1:1 ratio in Tunisia, which indicates that some citizens hold multiple phone subscriptions. Internet plans for phones are expensive, which has kept many Tunisians from using these devices to access websites. Most use the Internet at work, in cafés known as &lt;i&gt;publinets&lt;/i&gt;, or through USB adapters that connect their computers to 3G data networks &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Tunisia,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; Internet Freedom &lt;/h2&gt; &lt;a name=&quot;freedom-house&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Freedom House, an independent watchdog organization, created an index that measures Internet and digital media freedom by three criteria:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;b&gt;Obstacles to access&lt;/b&gt;: &quot;infrastructural and economic barriers to access, legal and ownership control over internet service providers (ISPs), and independence of regulatory bodies&quot;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;b&gt;Limits on content&lt;/b&gt;: &quot;legal regulations on content, technical filtering and blocking of websites, self-censorship, the vibrancy/diversity of online news media, and the use of ICTs for civic mobilization&quot;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;b&gt;Violations of user rights&lt;/b&gt;: &quot;surveillance, privacy, and repercussions for online activity, such as imprisonment, extralegal harassment, or cyber attacks&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom&quot;&gt;(“Freedom on the Net,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The scores from these three categories are added to get a &lt;b&gt;Freedom on the Net Total&lt;/b&gt;, which determines the status level of the country&#39;s Internet freedom—from &lt;i&gt;Free&lt;/i&gt;, like Canada, to &lt;i&gt;Not Free&lt;/i&gt;, like China.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tunisia&#39;s seen great improvements in its score, moving from its position as an &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/26/smau-background-tunisia#enemy&quot;&gt;Internet Enemy&lt;/a&gt; to a partially free country over the course of a few years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;
    &lt;small&gt;
    &lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
      &lt;b&gt;Table 2.&lt;/b&gt; Freedom on the Net &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Tunisia,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;2014&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Obstacles to access &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0=best, 25=worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Limits on content &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0=best, 35=worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Violations of user rights &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0=best, 40=worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Freedom total &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;(0=best, 100=worst)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;41&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Freedom status&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Not Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;Partly Free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Obstacles to access, limits on content, and violations of user rights have decreased fairly consistently in Tunisia. Freedom House even notes that the new constitution passed in 2014 protects free speech, privacy of communication data, and bans historic censorship laws on media. They do warn, however, that laws still exist that make defamation, insulting the state, and offending religion illegal. Additionally, access to the Internet is prohibitively expensive for many Tunisians, thanks to an underdeveloped infrastructure and a monopoly on international communications cables by Tunisie Télécom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some human rights organizations have expressed concerns about the newly established Technical Telecommunications Agency (ATT). It has been likened to the United States&#39; National Security Agency (NSA) because of the body&#39;s autonomy from government intervention and because the agency&#39;s actions are not open to public inquiry &lt;a href=&quot;#freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;(“Freedom House | Tunisia,” 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tunisia has seen some of the most significant progress toward open, pluralist reforms in the region post-Arab uprisings. As access to mobile and Internet resources increases, more Tunisians—including politicians—appear to be adopting forms of open discourse on socio-political issues. They have also recently used social media to unite in solidarity against the terrorist attack at the Bardo museum in March 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;#mackey&quot;&gt;(Mackey, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;:

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nous n&amp;#39;avons pas peur. We are not afraid. مناش خائفين &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/TnArp?src=hash&quot;&gt;#TnArp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Bardo?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Bardo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Tounes?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Tounes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sayida Ounissi (@SaidaOunissi) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SaidaOunissi/status/578178982165753856&quot;&gt;March 18, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;small&gt; Sayida Ounissi is a member of the Tunisian Parliament. &lt;/small&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Shortly thereafter, a wave of support came for Tunisia&#39;s tourism industry when users worldwide proclaimed #IWillComeToTunisia despite the attack &lt;a href=&quot;#king&quot;&gt;(King, 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Narratives of social good and of transnational solidarity are inspiring and offer great examples of the promise of social media. We have the potential to connect with each other as humans, despite physical and ideological separations. Though translation services are still far from perfect, not even language barriers are as daunting as they once were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tunisia&amp;#39;s progress toward free access to the Internet is substantial, but the volatility of that freedom can be seen in concerns expressed about the ATT, which some believe threatens to reverse everything accomplished over the past few years. John Oliver&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XEVlyP4_11M&quot;&gt;interview of Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; takes a comical approach to discussing the surveillance capabilities of the NSA, but a serious message stands out: if we don&amp;#39;t involve ourselves in the decisions our representatives make about our rights, we risk seeing a reversal of privileges and freedoms we take for granted—like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/issues/net-neutrality&quot;&gt;uninhibited access to content on the Internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Next up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the role of social media in Egypt today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr&quot;&gt;Arab Social Media Report. (2015). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.arabsocialmediareport.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;freedom-tunisia&quot;&gt;Freedom House | Tunisia. (2015). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedomhouse.org/country/tunisia#.VSmFKBPF-Uc&quot;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/country/tunisia#.VSmFKBPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-internet&quot;&gt;Percentage of individuals using the Internet. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI99H#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;un-mobile&quot;&gt;Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants. (2015). United Nations. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&quot;&gt;http://data.un.org/Data.aspx?d=ITU&amp;amp;f=ind1Code%3aI911#ITU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;asmr14&quot;&gt;Citizen Engagement and Public Services in the Arab World: The Potential of Social Media. (2014, June). Dubai School of Government. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.mbrsg.ae/getattachment/e9ea2ac8-13dd-4cd7-9104-b8f1f405cab3/Citizen-Engagement-and-Public-Services-in-the-Arab.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;freedom&quot;&gt;Freedom on the Net. (2015). Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedomhouse.org/report-types/freedom-net#.VSnbPhPF-Uc&quot;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/report-types/freedom-net#.VSnbPhPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abrougui&quot;&gt;Abrougui, A. (2015). Inaccurate Reports of ‘ISIS Taking Over Star Wars Set’ Anger Tunisians. &lt;i&gt;GlobalVoices&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/03/27/inaccurate-reports-of-isis-taking-over-star-wars-set-angers-tunisians/&quot;&gt;https://globalvoicesonline.org/2015/03/27/inaccurate-reports-of-isis-taking-over-star-wars-set-angers-tunisians/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abrougui13&quot;&gt;Abrougui, A. (2013). Tunisia Embraces Internet Freedom. &lt;i&gt;Social Media Exchange&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smex.org/tunisia-embraces-internet-freedom/&quot;&gt;http://www.smex.org/tunisia-embraces-internet-freedom/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mackey&quot;&gt;Mackey, R. (2015). Social Media Images of Antiterrorism Rally in Tunis. &lt;i&gt;New York Times&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/19/world/africa/social-media-images-of-antiterrorism-rally-in-tunis.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/19/world/africa/social-media-images-of-antiterrorism-rally-in-tunis.html?_r=1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/12/smau-sm-today-tunisia/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/12/smau-sm-today-tunisia/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Social Media in Libya</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Libya&amp;#39;s uprisings began shortly after Mubarak was overthrown in Egypt. Like Mubarak, Gaddafi shut down Internet and mobile phone networks inside of Libya early on in the conflicts, signaling that he, like Mubarak, was aware of the dangerous potential those resources had if used against him. Analysts considered this approach and offered several common observations about social media&amp;#39;s role in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Double-edged sword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morozov provided examples of ways in which media technology could be used against citizens in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/07/smau-analyses-egypt#monitor&quot;&gt;Egypt&lt;/a&gt;. He also noted that Gaddafi&amp;#39;s vast spying apparatus was known to monitor text messages, emails, and online chats &lt;a href=&quot;#morozov&quot;&gt;(Morozov, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. His regime sent text messages to threaten citizens and warn of the consequences of using social media to encourage protests. And, as was done in &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/04/07/smau-analyses-egypt#twitter&quot;&gt;Egypt&lt;/a&gt;, the Gaddafi regime sent out Twitter-like text notifications in an attempt to rally supporters &lt;a href=&quot;#beaumont&quot;&gt;(Beaumont, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. Activists using Facebook to demand Gaddafi&amp;#39;s resignation were arrested &lt;a href=&quot;#olivos&quot;&gt;(PaPaioannou &amp;amp; Olivos, 2013, p. 100)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media technology also created problems for those attempting to help Libyans. Humanitarian efforts like the Libya Crisis Map found that an overload of information via social media actually made it difficult for them to manage and verify the information they required to deploy aid to areas that were in need &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 9)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Social media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Internet conviviality creates unity and has democratising power that can be shared beyond what in the real world would be the traditional barriers of social and economic standing, cultural similarities and national and regional boundaries. But the Libya example has highlighted an even greater observation: that Internet conviviality can be experienced beyond Internet connectedness&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, pp. 10-11)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading up to the uprisings of 2011, only 14% of Libyans had access to the Internet. Gaddafi started shutting down Libya&amp;#39;s Internet services on February 18th; they were almost entirely disabled from the beginning of March until the end of the revolution. However, protest movements increased in size and momentum despite Internet and phone network shutdowns. Those who had access to the Internet used it to spread news about conflicts. Those who didn&amp;#39;t would collect video and photos on their mobile phones, and some would then exchange their SIM cards with people at the country&amp;#39;s borders who could upload data on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International media outlets, members of the Libyan Diaspora, and Libyans within the country all joined together to call for a &amp;quot;Day of Rage&amp;quot; against the regime on Februry 17th, but protests began in Benghazi two days prior to that, and the video footage collected during those events was used to increase awareness and improve the movement&amp;#39;s credibility &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 4)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter became a useful, low bandwidth tool inside of the country for sharing news with the outside world in short bursts. Medical needs, contact information, and satellite frequencies were also shared through such channels. One of the largest social media presences during the uprisings was the Libyan Youth Movement (LYM), which was comprised mostly of members of the Libyan diaspora. They used their large following on Twitter to disseminate messages on behalf of Libyans inside of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Diaspora&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libyan diaspora&amp;#39;s role in the Libyan revolution was regarded as highly significant. The Libyan Youth Movement as well as families and friends abroad facilitated communications between Libya and the international community, especially after the Internet and mobile networks were shut down &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 5)&lt;/a&gt;. Satellite communications, landlines, Skype, and mobile phones were used to pass messages along. These were often encoded in order to avoid detection by Gaddafi&amp;#39;s surveillance teams. Morris noted that &amp;quot;What was unexpected was how these connections would feed back directly to those within Libya, that the activist reports coming from within Libya but censored in Libya could be reported outside of Libya and beamed back in to generate more activism. A complete circle&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 10)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dedication of diaspora members and citizen journalists inside of Libya played a role that Morris believed could not be overstated &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 10)&lt;/a&gt;. She argued that, contrary to Malcolm Gladwell&amp;#39;s assertion that social media campaigns lacked structure and hierarchical strength, the complex network of communications developed between entities within and outside of Libya illustrated that a rigid, persistent campaign &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be established &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 10)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Journalists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information coming out of Libya was limited by Gaddafi&amp;#39;s restriction of the Internet and monitoring of phone lines, but social media was still used to report from within, and then mainstream media augmented those messages effectively enough to get international attention and intervention. Morris suggested that the reason why so many Libyans participated in protests was, at least in part, due to what they had seen on satellite television about the uprisings in neighboring countries. Satellite stations like Al Jazeera shared videos and posts culled from social media in their news feeds, which further connected Libyans even if they had no access to the Internet &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 6)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;journalists&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;When Gaddafi blocked all outsiders from entering the country, citizen journalists stepped in to ensure that the Libyan uprisings were reported. They did this at great personal risk, putting themselves in between three warring groups: Gaddafi&amp;#39;s army, freedom fighters, and allied foreign troops &lt;a href=&quot;#stream&quot;&gt;(“Libya’s New Citizen Journalists,” 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. Alternative and independent media outlets such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://original.livestream.com/libya17feb&quot;&gt;Libya Alhurra&lt;/a&gt; developed in Benghazi and transmitted footage of conflict via satellite Internet connections &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, pp. 4-5)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;340&quot; src=&quot;http://cdn.livestream.com/embed/libya17feb?layout=4&amp;amp;height=340&amp;amp;width=560&amp;amp;autoplay=false&quot; style=&quot;border:0;outline:0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mohammed Nabbous, founder of Libya Alhurra, is one of the most well known citizen journalists in Libya&amp;#39;s revolution. He was killed by snipers on March 19, 2011.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morris spoke of the potential impact of such citizen-driven efforts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evidence coming from citizen journalists of state inflicted violence does not necessarily lead to international support in the form of military intervention. The unprecedented use of R2P [Responsibility to Protect] in the case of Libya may more closely reflect the international communities sentiments towards the Gaddafi regime itself than any direct empathy with the Libyan people. It is novel nonetheless that the international community found justification for action within the citizen journalist reports coming from Libya; new media reporting of the crisis therefore may have been the final invitation to act &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 8)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When eastern Libya was liberated by rebel fighters, international press and mainstream media organizations took over the role that citizen journalists had filled in their absence. Social media continued to be relied upon as a source of information by media channels &lt;a href=&quot;#morris&quot;&gt;(Morris, 2014, p. 7)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed at which information can be spread is likely to be the greatest strength and weakness of social media. It disseminated information about what was happening inside of Libya across the globe at a rate that Gaddafi, despite all of his sophisticated efforts, could not stop. The rate at which information was disseminated also complicated humanitarian efforts on the ground in Libya, making it more difficult for aid workers to determine where they most needed to deploy their resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note is the fact that a nearly continuous deficit of reliable access to Internet and mobile networks did not result in an end to the Libyan movement. Protestors still found ways to get messages out of the country, and once that information was out, it was spread by a broad network of allies as well as members of the Libyan diaspora. Social networks—both on and offline—played important roles in Libya&amp;#39;s revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at the role of social media in Tunisia today. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;beaumont&quot;&gt;Beaumont, P. (2011). The truth about Twitter, Facebook and the uprisings in the Arab world. &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/25/twitter-facebook-uprisings-arab-libya&quot;&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/25/twitter-facebook-uprisings-arab-libya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;async&quot;&gt;Asynchronous Social Media. (2013). Small World News. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://smallworldnews.tv/featured/asynchronous-social-media/&quot;&gt;http://smallworldnews.tv/featured/asynchronous-social-media/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;storck&quot;&gt;Storck, M. (2011). &lt;i&gt;The Role of Social Media in Political Mobilisation: a Case Study of the January 2011 Egyptian Uprising&lt;/i&gt; (dissertation). University of St Andrews, Scotland. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/2012-02-bifef/The_Role_of_Social_Media_in_Political_Mobilisation_-_Madeline_Storck.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/2012-02-bifef/The_Role_of_Social_Media_in_Political_Mobilisation_-_Madeline_Storck.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;khamis&quot;&gt;Khamis, S., &amp;amp; Vaughn, K. (2011). ‘we are all Khaled said’:
the potentials and limitations of cyberactivism in triggering public mobilization and promoting political change. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Arab &amp;Amp; Muslim Media Research&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;4&lt;/i&gt;(2 &amp;amp; 3), 145–163. Retrieved from &lt;10.1386/jammr.4.2-3.145_1&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;fish&quot;&gt;Srinivasan, R., &amp;amp; Fish, A. (2011, November). Revolutionary Tactics, Media Ecologies, and Repressive States. Public Culture. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://publicculture.org/articles/view/23/3/revolutionary-tactics-media-ecologies-and-repressive-states&quot;&gt;http://publicculture.org/articles/view/23/3/revolutionary-tactics-media-ecologies-and-repressive-states&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;morozov&quot;&gt;Morozov, E. (2011). Political Repression 2.0. &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt;, 23.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;olivos&quot;&gt;PaPaioannou, T., &amp;amp; Olivos, H. E. (2013). Cultural identity and social media in the arab spring: Collective goals in the use of Facebook in the libyan context. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Arab &amp;Amp; Muslim Media Research&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;6&lt;/i&gt;(2 &amp;amp; 3), 99–114. Retrieved from &lt;10.1386/jammr.6.2-3.99_1&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nsir&quot;&gt;Nsir, N. (2014). The perceptions of social media in Libya. &lt;i&gt;ProQuest Dissertations and Theses&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from http://login.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/login?url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/1660972391?accountid=4485&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;morris&quot;&gt;Morris, L. (2014). Contextualizing the power of social media: Technology, communication and the Libya Crisis. &lt;i&gt;First Monday&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;19&lt;/i&gt;(12). Retrieved from http://journals.uic.edu/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/5318&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;el-kasm&quot;&gt;El Kasm, S. (2011). &lt;i&gt;Rebuilding Libya&lt;/i&gt; (p. 1). Inter-Hemispheric Resource Center Press. Retrieved from http://login.ezproxy1.lib.asu.edu/login?url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/909052797?accountid=4485&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/10/smau-analyses-libya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/10/smau-analyses-libya/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media and the Arab Uprisings: Social Media in Egypt</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many analysts have spoken confidently about the positive role that social media played in the Egyptian revolution of 2011, but potentially negative aspects of the relationship were addressed, as well. We&amp;#39;ll cover several common points in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Blogs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt&amp;#39;s policies for online content were considerably less restrictive than Tunisia&amp;#39;s. Prior to the protests in early 2011, Egypt didn&amp;#39;t formally censor websites or content. Instead, Mubarak&amp;#39;s security forces monitored communications and then harassed and imprisoned activists—a different approach to censorship than that employed by Ben Ali&amp;#39;s regime. Despite this, a lively community of users and political bloggers blossomed starting around 2005. This allowed Egyptians to increase political awareness, communicate with other activists, and freely spread ideas of hope and change &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, pp. 1277-1282)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Social networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;small&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Platforms like YouTube, Twitter, Facebook were helping us a lot because it basically gave us the impression that, &amp;#39;Wow, I&amp;#39;m not alone. There are a lot of people who are frustrated&amp;#39;&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#ghonim&quot;&gt;(Ghonim, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 17% of Egypt&amp;#39;s population were connected to the Internet at home; even more connected in Internet cafes. Facebook was the most popular social networking site, with almost 5 million users—approximately 22% of all Facebook users in the region &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, p. 1277)&lt;/a&gt;. Its role in the mobilization of protestors for the &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#april6&quot;&gt;riots on April 6, 2008&lt;/a&gt; signaled a shift toward social networking rather than blogging &lt;a href=&quot;#sarnelli&quot;&gt;(Sarnelli, 2013, p. 160)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Facebook and Twitter were used to announce the details of demonstrations and spread images of the regime&amp;#39;s corruption as well as its abuse of Egyptians. Twitter was identified as a crucial enough resource for protestors that Mubarak&amp;#39;s regime ordered mobile service providers to send out notifications like those sent by Twitter to rally his own supporters &lt;a href=&quot;#beaumont&quot;&gt;(Beaumont, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook pages like &lt;em&gt;We are all Khaled Said&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;April 6 Youth Movement&lt;/em&gt; were increasingly used as resources for seeking and sharing knowledge among activists, both inside and out of Egypt. Within 6 weeks of the start of protests on January 25th, 357,000 followers on the &lt;em&gt;We are all Khaled Said&lt;/em&gt; Facebook page had grown to 1,026,000. Srinivasan asserted that this is what social media did best: it interconnected the local and the global; it helped protesters think and communicate &lt;em&gt;across&lt;/em&gt; rather than simply &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; networks &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinke and Röder note, however, that &amp;quot;the spillover from the virtual spaces to the Egyptian streets would not have been possible without other communication technologies, such as mobile phones, e-mail, and satellite television channels&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, p. 1278)&lt;/a&gt;. At 72%, Egyptians&amp;#39; access to mobile phones was over four times greater than their access to the Internet &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, p. 1278)&lt;/a&gt;. Text messages and emails were used to pass sensitive information along within trusted, personal networks rather than via broad online networks like Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Mubarak&amp;#39;s regime shut down Internet and mobile phone networks, Egyptians found other ways to get their message out. For instance, an American student with friends in Egypt created a Twitter account called &lt;em&gt;Jan25voices&lt;/em&gt;, which he used to publish messages his friends relayed to him by phone &lt;a href=&quot;#sarnelli&quot;&gt;(Sarnelli, 2013, p. 166)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Al Jazeera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Televisions were said to be in every living room, coffee shop, store, and waiting room in Egypt. This afforded media outlets a distinct opportunity in the Egyptian revolutions. Contradictions between the state-run channels&amp;#39; coverage of protests and that of transnational stations such as Al Jazeera were laid bare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al Jazeera played a similar role in Egypt to that in Tunisia, positioning itself as a facilitator of two-way communication between protestors and the international public &lt;a href=&quot;#sarnelli&quot;&gt;(Sarnelli, 2013, p. 171)&lt;/a&gt;. Its broadcast of the protests started the day after the January 25th demonstrations, at which point it provided live broadcasting of the uprisings until Mubarak left office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The network established connections between countries in the region via its Arabic channels and outside of the region in English. Rinke and Röder emphasize the significance of this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arabs do not have to overcome a language barrier to a transnational public sphere, which likely was a significant factor leading to the popular spread of protest across country borders to Libya, Bahrain, and Syria, to name just the most visible examples...transnational news channels in the Arab region can be an important relay station for disseminating the idea of anti-authoritarian protest und renewing the idea of pan-Arabism in the struggle for freedom &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, p. 1280)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newer and older media converged when Al Jazeera reporters started collecting ideas for stories from Twitter. &amp;quot;This creates possibilities of things to move across cultural groups and make bridges between people across different segments of a population&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinke and Röder point out that oral communication was a critical component of the uprisings. One-to-one communication promoted the trust necessary to mobilize a greater number of people &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, p. 1275)&lt;/a&gt;. This was best exemplified in its use during Friday Mosque, where citizens congregated after prayers to discuss political issues. On &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/29/smau-background-egypt#jan28&quot;&gt;Friday, January 28th&lt;/a&gt;, Internet and mobile phone networks had been shut down. Egyptians gathered after prayers to protest the regime, calling it a &lt;em&gt;Day of Anger&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt&amp;#39;s revolution drew generations of different socio-economic backgrounds and ideologies together. Wael Ghonim spoke to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who would [have] imagined before the 25th, if I tell you that hundreds of thousands of Christians are going to pray and tens of thousands of Muslims are going to protect them, and then hundreds of thousands of Muslims are going to pray and tens of thousands of Christians are going to protect them—this is amazing. All the stereotypes that the regime was trying to put on us through their so-called propaganda, or mainstream media, are proven wrong. This whole revolution showed us how ugly such a regime was and how great and amazing the Egyptian man, the Egyptian woman, how simple and amazing these people are whenever they have a dream &lt;a href=&quot;#ghonim&quot;&gt;(Ghonim, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Double-edged sword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;monitor&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Social media has been presented as a potent weapon against authoritarian regimes, but Morozov warned that it has also been effectively used by governments to monitor and suppress citizens. For instance, in Egypt, it was discovered that Mubarak&amp;#39;s regime had been testing a tool developed by a Western company that allowed them to eavesdrop on Skype conversations, which were thought to be immune from wiretapping. This, Morozov said, isn&amp;#39;t uncommon. The Egyptian government also used Internet traffic surveillance tools sold by Narus, a company owned by Boeing &lt;a href=&quot;#morozov2011&quot;&gt;(Morozov, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;quot;Left uncontrolled, Western surveillance tools could undermine the Internet freedom agenda in the same way arms exports undermine Western-led peace initiatives&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;#morozov&quot;&gt;(Morozov, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinke and Röder added that, rather than shutting down online forums, the Egyptian regime&amp;#39;s supporters interfered with discussions by spreading rumors meant to increase confusion and anxiety; text messages were sent to Egyptian mobile phones when the networks were disabled for public use, warning of pillagings and encouraging recipients to stay home and protect their families and property &lt;a href=&quot;#rinke&quot;&gt;(Rinke &amp;amp; Röder, 2011, pp. 1281-1282)&lt;/a&gt;. Srinivasan also warned of the danger of echo chambers—if you surround yourself with only those who share the same ideas as yourself, you risk the likelihood of distorting your perception of reality &lt;a href=&quot;#srinivasan&quot;&gt;(Srinivasan, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fukuyama&amp;#39;s critique of social media&amp;#39;s role in Egypt questioned next steps in institution building:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook, which went public last week, has been credited with helping to build democracy internationally. It is true that it and other social media have democratized access to information, and have made collaboration easier. These media have also helped promote short-term mobilization of crowds and demonstrators. But networking is not organization-building. For that, we need a different and more durable platform &lt;a href=&quot;#fukuyama&quot;&gt;(Fukuyama, 2012)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Srinivasan&amp;#39;s warning that social media can create echo chambers and distort our perception of reality is one most can likely relate to. In Egypt, Twitter users were generally more well off, stayed toward the back of the crowd during protests, and tweeted about freedom while those with lower incomes protested the price of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/2011/08/12/139570720/twitter-created-echo-chamber-during-egyptian-protests&quot;&gt;food&lt;/a&gt;. Neither stance is invalid, but to present only one side as the cause of the revolution would be false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Echo chambers are a legitimate threat, perpetuated by the speed at which messages spread via social media. For example, regardless of your stance on Indiana and Arkansas&amp;#39; recently passed Religious Freedom Restoration Acts, you&amp;#39;ll most likely concede that echo chambers exist and have distorted the reality of the situation on the ground. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indystar.com/story/news/politics/2015/04/01/rfra-boycotts-bans-growing-backlash/70810178/&quot;&gt;Withholding all business&lt;/a&gt; from a state hurts the state &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; its inhabitants, including those within the LGBT community that live and work there. Lumping all of the LGBT community into one &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bryanjfischer/status/582952288253247488&quot;&gt;indistinguishable mass&lt;/a&gt; strips individuals of their humanity, rationalizing and justifying unequal treatment. The end result is that subsets of the same species are driven further and further apart; interactions and communications become harder to maintain. I&amp;#39;ve written about how effective it was for dictators to maintain power by promoting &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/26/smau-background-tunisia#divide-and-conquer&quot;&gt;divisions&lt;/a&gt; among their citizens. Why should we think that divisions don&amp;#39;t weaken us as a nation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll look at different analyses of social media&amp;#39;s role in the uprisings in Libya. See &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/arab-uprisings/summary&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;rinke&quot;&gt;Rinke, E. M., &amp;amp; Röder, M. (2011). Media Ecologies, Communication Culture, and Temporal-Spatial Unfolding: Three Components in a Communication Model of the Egyptian Regime Change. &lt;i&gt;International Journal of Communication&lt;/i&gt;, (5), 1273–1285.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;sarnelli&quot;&gt;Sarnelli, V. (2013). Tunisia, Egypt and the voices of the revolution in Al Jazeera English. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Arab &amp;Amp; Muslim Media Research&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;6&lt;/i&gt;(2&amp;amp;3), 157–176. Retrieved from &lt;10.1386/jammr.6.2-3.157_1&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;beaumont&quot;&gt;Beaumont, P. (2011). The truth about Twitter, Facebook and the uprisings in the Arab world. &lt;i&gt;The Guardian&lt;/i&gt;. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/25/twitter-facebook-uprisings-arab-libya&quot;&gt;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/25/twitter-facebook-uprisings-arab-libya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;srinivasan&quot;&gt;Srinivasan, R. (2012, November). Digital Dissent and People’s Power. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NQXbMLtiB-0&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NQXbMLtiB-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;popovic&quot;&gt;Popovic, S. (2011, November). How to Topple a Dictator. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks/srdja_popovic_how_to_topple_a_dictator/transcript?language=en&quot;&gt;http://www.ted.com/talks/srdja_popovic_how_to_topple_a_dictator/transcript?language=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ghonim&quot;&gt;Ghonim, W. (2011, March). Inside the Egyptian Revolution. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks/wael_ghonim_inside_the_egyptian_revolution/transcript?language=en&quot;&gt;http://www.ted.com/talks/wael_ghonim_inside_the_egyptian_revolution/transcript?language=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;morozov&quot;&gt;Morozov, E. (2011). Political Repression 2.0. &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt;, 23.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;morozov2011&quot;&gt;Morozov, E. (2011, March). The internet is a tyrant’s friend. New Scientist. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg20928026.100-the-internet-is-a-tyrants-friend.html#.VSBj0pPF-Uc&quot;&gt;http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg20928026.100-the-internet-is-a-tyrants-friend.html#.VSBj0pPF-Uc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;fukuyama&quot;&gt;Fukuyama, F. (2012, May). The Failures of the Facebook Generation in the Arab Spring. The Daily Beast. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/05/21/the-failures-of-the-facebook-generation-in-the-arab-spring.html&quot;&gt;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/05/21/the-failures-of-the-facebook-generation-in-the-arab-spring.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;elazari&quot;&gt;Elazari, K. (2014, April). Internet access is a basic human right: A Q&amp;amp;A with Keren Elazari. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ted.com/turkey-banned-twitter-keren-elazari/&quot;&gt;http://blog.ted.com/turkey-banned-twitter-keren-elazari/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;elazari2014&quot;&gt;Elazari, K. (2014, March). Some hackers are bad. But a lot are good: Keren Elazari at TED2014. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ted.com/some-hackers-are-bad-but-a-lot-are-good-keren-elazari-at-ted2014/&quot;&gt;http://blog.ted.com/some-hackers-are-bad-but-a-lot-are-good-keren-elazari-at-ted2014/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;storck&quot;&gt;Storck, M. (2011). &lt;i&gt;The Role of Social Media in Political Mobilisation: a Case Study of the January 2011 Egyptian Uprising&lt;/i&gt; (dissertation). University of St Andrews, Scotland. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/2012-02-bifef/The_Role_of_Social_Media_in_Political_Mobilisation_-_Madeline_Storck.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.culturaldiplomacy.org/academy/content/pdf/participant-papers/2012-02-bifef/The_Role_of_Social_Media_in_Political_Mobilisation_-_Madeline_Storck.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;howard&quot;&gt;Howard, P., &amp;amp; Hussain, M. (2011). The Role of Digital Media. &lt;i&gt;Journal of Democracy&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;22&lt;/i&gt;(3), 35–48. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&quot;http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/jod/summary/v022/22.3.howard.html&quot;&gt;http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/jod/summary/v022/22.3.howard.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hussain&quot;&gt;Hussain, M. (2014). Digital Infrastructure Politics and Internet Freedom Stakeholders After the Arab Spring. &lt;i&gt;Journal o FInternational Affairs&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;68&lt;/i&gt;(1), 37–56.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/07/smau-analyses-egypt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.elisabethgray.me//2015/04/07/smau-analyses-egypt/</guid>
        
        <category>arab-uprisings</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
