<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-13T13:20:10-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/</id><title type="html">Elisabeth Gray</title><subtitle>Academic and personal work with a bent toward technology, communication, culture, and conflict.</subtitle><author><name>ECG</name></author><entry><title type="html">Balkans Detour: Venice</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/venice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Balkans Detour: Venice" /><published>2017-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-03-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/venice</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/venice/"># Venice

We took a day trip to Venice with a group of five other people in between our adventures in Slovenia. Ambroz, our guide from [Roundabout travel](http://www.travel-slovenia.com/day-tours/public-regular-tours/venice/) picked us up at 8am. We parked around 11 and walked into the city via the [Constitution Bridge](https://www.google.com/maps/place/Constitution+Bridge/@45.4389021,12.3179276,18.32z/data=!4m13!1m7!3m6!1s0x477eaa16cb134829:0x307098715907f10!2sMetropolitan+City+of+Venice,+Italy!3b1!8m2!3d45.4930475!4d12.4177003!3m4!1s0x0:0xeab1f25258fa1c5a!8m2!3d45.4388094!4d12.3194108) over the Grand Canal.

In essence, this was the first time either of us had _seen_ Venice: It was my actual first visit to the city, but on her last visit as a moderately rebellious 14 year old, Rachel decided to leave her glasses at home. It didn't work out well for her.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

Though we were told that the crowds were pretty light, they seemed quite heavy at times. In the more touristy areas of the city, there were loads of people in gondolas who'd paid 80 Euro for a 20-minute ride and probably didn't move more than a few hundred feet. We opted not to spend money on that experience.

Glory be to glasses, Rachel got to appreciate the detail in St. Mark's Cathedral this time around. It was magnificent and very crowded.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

After a brief tour with our guide, we took to the less-trafficked streets on our own, ate at a little café by a campo, or square, and then wandered around.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

{% archive_audio venice-campo %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Musicians in a campo in Venice&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The city was really charming. Each street had a slightly different look and feel. We found some with art shops and wine stores, others with laundry hanging out to dry on lines overhead, some that ended in canals, and we even witnessed someone throwing a key down from the second floor to a person at ground level so they could let themselves in.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

{% archive_audio along-venice-canal %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sounds from along a canal in Venice&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

After several hours, we met up with our group and took a water taxi back to the area where we parked. The taxis are the same type of boats used in James Bond's speed boat chase, though they never go very fast. It was a great way to see the city, and it cost significantly less at 12 Euro per person.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

The trip lasted about twelve hours total and was a great way to get a feel for the city. Next time we visit, we'll head straight to the [Peggy Guggenheim Collection](http://www.guggenheim-venice.it/default.html) and we'll also check out [La Bienniale](http://www.labiennale.org/en/Home.html).

# The End
This marks the end of my posts on our fall 2016 trip to the Balkans and Venice. Stay tuned for reports from the next adventure.</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Slovenia</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/slovenia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Slovenia" /><published>2017-02-26T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/slovenia</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/slovenia/"># Slovenia
Aside from a 30-minute stop at the Croatian-Slovenian border where passports and the train itself were inspected, we spent most of our time watching and listening to cities and countryside pass us by on our way to Ljubljana.

{% archive_audio train-zagreb-ljubljana %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sounds on the train ride from Zagreb to Ljubljana&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

{% include video id=&quot;A2wyjb2jn7Q&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

## Ljubljana
Our host had a taxi-driving friend pick us up from the train station and take us to our Airbnb, which was attached to the host's place of employment: a coffee shop and bar filled with a reasonable sampling of working-class folks. We were located within walking distance of Ljublana's center. On our first night, we were greeted by vivid cloudscapes, little workers on sewage covers, and an incredible dinner at [Le Petit Cafe](https://www.facebook.com/lepetitcafeljubljana/).

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

We also explored the old part of the city and found lots of cute shops, bars, art, and musicians near the canal.
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

{% archive_audio ljubljana-centar %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Street musician playing along the canal in Ljubljana's city center&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

## Vintgar Gorge
We rented a car to visit a few places elsewhere in Slovenia. The roads and scenery were impressive, as was our little [Opel Adam](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opel_Adam), which handled mountain inclines much better than the previous car.

[Vintgar gorge](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vintgar_Gorge) was the first destination on a whirlwind day trip. It's tucked into the far east corner of [Triglav National Park](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triglav_National_Park), whose namesake is the highest mountain of the [Julian Alps](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_Alps) at about 9,400 feet tall. Triglav is also featured in [Slovenia's coat of arms](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coat_of_arms_of_Slovenia).

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

Look closely at the banks to see the piles of stones people have stacked along the river in the video below.

{% include video id=&quot;XP_0uXrgmjw&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

On our way down the gorge, we spotted what we think was a [marten](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_pine_marten) along the bank of the river on the opposite side. As we passed back through on our return trip, the marten decided to take a swim and say hello from a little bit closer.

{% include video id=&quot;2_ARXh22QGw&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

## Lake Bled
We went from Vintgar gorge to Lake Bled, which was about 15 minutes away. Because we had a dinner reservation at [Hiša Franko](http://www.hisafranko.com/en/) later that evening, we stayed long enough to take pictures, eat a piece of Lake Bled's famed cream cake, and drink a coffee.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-7&quot; %}

## Hiša Franko
We (ignorantly) thought the drive from Ljubljana to Hiša Franko would be a simple two hour drive there and then back. As we left the highway for country roads, it became apparent that the drive might not be as simple as we thought in the dark and after a large meal. [This was our route.](https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Ljubljana,+Slovenia/Hi%C5%A1a+Franko,+Staro+selo,+Kobarid,+Slovenia/@46.071349,13.7569024,10.65z/data=!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x476531f5969886d1:0x400f81c823fec20!2m2!1d14.5057515!2d46.0569465!1m5!1m1!1s0x477a5b50b0926c83:0x644c869c3c6f2f8!2m2!1d13.537986!2d46.247005!3e0) Be sure to zoom in for get a better idea of the fun we had.

Dark clouds _sometimes_ gathered and wind _sometimes_ whipped over us while Triglav and the surrounding mountains loomed in the background; brief bursts of fear were balanced out with amazement at the scenery. I did my best to capture some of what we encountered but couldn't spare you the jostling of the camera resulting from wind. I did remove the sound to protect your ears.

{% include video id=&quot;FdgtGrIGIWo&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

{% include video id=&quot;n-rOL14GJz4&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

{% include video id=&quot;KQyUm9qj1Eo&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

At long last, we arrived at our destination:
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-8&quot; %}

We were, of course, the first guests to arrive for the evening. Rachel's enjoying the last of a parmesan popsicle in the image below. I still think about that bread on the table.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-9&quot; %}

If you enjoy fancy meals, check out the [Chef's Table episode on Ana Ros](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5762440/) and then promptly book your flight to Slovenia. It's an experience you will not regret. My only suggestion is that you opt to stay at the hotel on the premises rather than drive back to Ljubljana in the dark like Rachel and I did. [This part](https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Ljubljana,+Slovenia/Hi%C5%A1a+Franko,+Staro+selo,+Kobarid,+Slovenia/@45.970106,14.061979,15.65z/data=!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x476531f5969886d1:0x400f81c823fec20!2m2!1d14.5057515!2d46.0569465!1m5!1m1!1s0x477a5b50b0926c83:0x644c869c3c6f2f8!2m2!1d13.537986!2d46.247005!3e0) of our return trip was perhaps my favorite, particularly in combination with lane closures for construction. Rachel, hero of the evening, drove while I stared only at the map and attempted to warn her about what was coming next.

**Pro tip**: Sometimes Google maps downplay the severity of turns in the road. Take 'em slow.
{: .notice}

# Coming Soon
We took a day trip to [Venice](/venice) in between adventures in Slovenia. We'll end this blog series there!</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Zagreb</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/zagreb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Zagreb" /><published>2017-02-08T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-02-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/zagreb</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/zagreb/"># Zagreb
Rain followed us from Plitvice to Zagreb. We arrived late enough on a Sunday that we found a place to eat dinner, hung our wet clothes throughout the apartment in a vain attempt to dry them, were serenaded by a neighbor (listen below), and then went to bed.

{% archive_audio zagreb-always-love-you %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;A neighbor singing along with Whitney Houston's I Will Always Love You&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

It was still raining a little bit when we woke up. Zvonko, our host, lent us a couple of umbrellas, and we started our excursion. After breakfast, we wandered around the upper town, or old part of the city.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

We also visited two museums: [The Museum of Broken Relationships](https://brokenships.com/visit/museum-details) and [The Croatian Museum of Naïve Art](http://www.hmnu.hr/en). I recommend visiting both should you find yourself in Zagreb.

The Museum of Broken Relationships was filled with remnants of—you guessed it—relationships that had ended. Stories accompanied most of the artifacts and covered a broad range of emotions: funny, sincere, sad, poetic.

The Croatian Museum of Naïve Art is a small building with a well-curated collection of work focused on a period in the 20th century when a group of untrained painters and sculptors developed their own conceptual approach to art. The [museum's site](http://www.hmnu.hr/en/naive_art/131/2) sums this up better than I can:

The Naive is the consequence and proof of democratisation in both the general relations in society and in artistic creation. It clearly shows that everyone has the right to express himself or herself in art and that schools of art are in themselves no guarantee of artistic value, because art can be created even without them. In the Naive, emotion counts more than reason and intellectual speculations. In the majority of cases, the Naive expresses the joy of life and the victory of hope. Here we can discover &quot;the forgotten nature&quot; and &quot;lost childhood&quot;, stories and dreams, a vital imagination and simple human inventions, the forgotten &quot;wonder at the world&quot; and the ability to rejoice in motif. But the Naive is not just an Arcadian art and idyll, it does not express only trust in and celebration of life; there are some sorry tales in it too, some dark and chthonic accords; in the Naive we can also come across the tragic and the symbolic, the fantastic and the irreal, surreal relationships, somnambulism and unreality, which all means that it is made up of a hundred opposites, just like Life.
{: .notice}

The color and detail of the art was made even more pronounced by the fact that many pieces were painted onto glass.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

Zagreb's an interesting city. It reminded me of somewhere I'd been before but also felt completely foreign. Austria-Hungary's influence on the city is clear, but it was when we were walking through Ban Jelačić Square that it hit me: the city has a similar feel to Paris. Musicians were playing music on the streets and in the squares; open markets and green spaces abound; art—commissioned and otherwise—covers most surfaces; and people sit outside at cafés, under blankets and heat lamps if necessary.

{% archive_audio teen-spirit-zagreb %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Street musicians in Zagreb performing a cover of Smells Like Teen Spirit; a tram passes by. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

We didn't know what to expect from Zagreb and consequently didn't devote enough time on this trip to it. It's on our list of places to return to, preferably when it's not raining.

# Zagreb to Ljubljana
[Zagreb Glavni kolodvor](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zagreb_Glavni_kolodvor) is the main hub of the Croatian railway network, and it's where we left Zagreb for Ljubljana, Slovenia. One of the first things we found was the passport photo booth:

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

We also bought books, burek, and coffee. We had a reasonable amount of time to kill while waiting for our train to arrive, so I made surreal art by misusing the pano mode on my phone.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}

We had a compartment to ourselves on the train, which afforded us the opportunity for further mischief and photo-taking.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-7&quot; %}

# Coming Soon
We'll cross the border into [Slovenia](/slovenia) on the train and then share more from our time in [Ljubljana](/slovenia/#ljubljana) and beyond.</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Plitvice</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/plitvice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Plitvice" /><published>2017-02-04T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-02-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/plitvice</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/plitvice/"># Driving North
We drove through periods of rain and high winds as we left Split and headed through the mountains to Plitvice. Tunnels allowed us to cut through without too many sharp turns, though our little [Opel Astra](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opel_Astra) struggled to accelerate up the steeper inclines.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

We eventually left the highway for scenic country roads intermittently interrupted by small towns.

{% include video id=&quot;rQXhYRccjJg&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

One of the first towns I remember encountering was Korenica, which is right along the border of Bosnia-Herzegovina near Bihać. This region was central to [Operation Storm](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Storm), one of the last major operations of the Croatian war and a strategic victory in the Bosnian war. The Serb army appears to have used this town as a base during the wars. There were a lot of Orthodox graves and empty houses on one side of town, while the other side was newer and more developed.

# Plitvice National Park
**Obligatory Balkan war fact**: The first shots of the Croatian war for independence in 1991 were [fired at Plitvice](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plitvice_Lakes_incident).
{: .notice}

I've never seen anything like what we saw here. Our first view was from a cliffside looking down at the lower lakes. Impending rain made the greens and blues feel deeper and more dramatic.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

As we wound down the path to the lakes, the colors and sounds became even more vivid. Our photos really don't do the experience justice.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

We entered the park early enough to avoid a lot of tourist traffic. It was still tricky to navigate past clusters of them on the narrow platforms, which allowed us to walk beside and across the lakes.

{% include video id=&quot;GmA81cvQ2-0&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

{% include video id=&quot;iogX65fGMU4&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

It started raining lightly, so Rachel and I moved quickly past the groups to get to the boats that would take us from the lower to the upper lakes.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

When we arrived at the boats, it started raining heavily and continued to do so for the remainder of our time in the park.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

The ride across the lake was very wet and very peaceful.

{% include video id=&quot;udYqvJlHceE&quot; provider=&quot;youtube&quot; %}

By this time in our journey, Rachel's rain jacket had decided to give up; water rushed through through a breach in the outer wall. We decided to catch a bus back to our entry and call it a day after we arrived on the other side of the lake.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}

We drove along more country roads and through fascinating looking little towns on our way from Plitvice to Zagreb. We thought we'd spotted a bear and two cubs not long after we'd departed Plitvice. To our embarassment, they were just incredibly realistic-looking cutouts in the rain. Slunj had some war memorials along the roadside, one of which was heavily tagged with graffiti. We also passed a town with war machinery on display in a yard along the road. The rain kept us from stopping for a closer look, so we've marked these locations for further exploration next time we visit.

# Coming Soon
Photos from our time in [Zagreb](/zagreb).</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Split</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/split/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Split" /><published>2017-01-29T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-01-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/split</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/split/"># Split
The ferry ride to Split was full without being uncomfortable. Rachel and I sat toward the bow, which afforded us a nice view of port entries and the sunset.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

Our neighbors included a couple with an energetic and charming child around 2 years old, a New Zealander toward the end of his post-college travels around the world, and his companion-of-the-moment who left the ferry in Hvar. The neighboring child commandeered the majority of our attention with her dancing and dramatic facial expressions, punctuated by spontaneous sprints down the aisles. Our friend from New Zealand seemed to be experiencing the worst hangover of his life and was trying to figure out whether he should book a room in a hostel or stay overnight in Split's airport for his early morning flight the following day.

The water was pretty choppy so the ferry couldn't run at full speed. We arrived about 45 minutes later than anticipated. Upon arrival, we walked from the harbor to our Airbnb, which was nested inside the maze of Roman cobblestone streets that is [Diocletian's palace](http://www.diocletianspalace.org/).

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

The pace and energy was a dramatic shift from the mellow vibe of Korčula. It was Saturday night. The city was filled with music coming from dance clubs as well as local performers. Gangs of teenagers roamed the streets looking for their next source of entertainment. People dined in restaurants and drank at bars tucked into every available corner of the old, walled downtown area.

Rachel and I went out for dinner at the quietest place we could find and were grateful that the windows in our apartment were incredibly effective at blocking out sound.

We left our apartment at 7:30 to get to the car rental by 8am. The streets we'd seen just hours before looked completely different when occupied primarily by pigeons.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

We walked along the eerily calm and empty harbor for about 10-15 minutes and passed storefronts, homes, and unoccupied buildings before reaching the car rental office. We were, of course, early enough that we beat the employees there. Rain threatened to make our wait outside uncomfortable, but it passed by without incident.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

We stopped into a [Konzum](https://www.konzum.hr/) (grocery store) to stock up on water and snacks on our way to the rental car pickup location, which was in a strip filled with half-finished structures a few blocks from the office. The lot attendants hung out on lawn chairs in one such hollowed-out building.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}

Split was a good stopping point for us on our trip north toward Plitvice and Zagreb. The history of Diocletian's palace is very interesting; the buildings and statues throughout are really beautiful. It is, however, very obviously a port city focused on appealing to tourists and party-goers.

# Coming Soon
Photos from our trip to [Plitvice](/plitvice).</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Korčula</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/korcula/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Korčula" /><published>2016-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/korcula</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/korcula/"># Korčula
Our catamaran to Korčula wasn't scheduled to depart until the early evening, so we walked around the Port of Dubrovnik, ate lunch at a [cute restaurant](http://www.tavernaotto.com/en/) on the bay, and then read by the hotel pool.

Our [hotel](http://www.berkeleyhotel.hr/) was very close to the port. This didn't keep us from being anxious about missing the boat, so we positioned ourselves at a café across from the dock an hour before boarding time and waited for the queue to start to build before heading over. Once onboard, Rachel snagged us a table spot along the windows on the upper deck, and we settled in for our two-hour trip.

## Airbnb
We took a speed boat taxi from the port in Korčula to our Airbnb. It was a fun, five-minute ride that cost about 100 kuna, or $13, which was well worth it. Though it would have only been a 20-minute walk, house addresses along the road didn't really exist and it was getting dark.

The taxi dropped us off on the little dock where the blue boat is tied up. Our apartment was the second (or first in European terms) floor of the house in front of the dock.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

This seems like an appropriate time to praise Rachel's apartment-hunting skills. The location was an excellent place to pause and relax. We spent mornings and evenings on the porch drinking Bosnian coffee and Croatian wine while listening to boats moving through the bay. The apartment was within walking distance of the old city, and we could swim whenever we wanted.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

We only ended up swimming in the bay outside our apartment once while on Korčula, but for no other reason than we opted to spend most of our time wandering around the old city and surrounding area. It felt like about 27°C/80°F in the sun, and the water was around 22°C/72°F. I took the GoPro in to experiment with shots underwater. The center photo, which I'll call housespongebee, is my favorite attempt at expressing my Surrealist self.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-7&quot; %}

### Cats
Our host was very kind to us and to those around her. She had somewhere around ten outdoor cats that she fed, so we had a lot of visitors. The main three are captured below. The grey cat made a surprise appearance in the apartment while we were reading one afternoon.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

## Old city
Korčula was a bit more expensive to dine and shop in than it had been in Sarajevo, though it was still less expensive than other port towns like Dubrovnik and Split. The old city wasn't very big, but there were lots of shops, restaurants, and galleries to explore.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

{% archive_audio bells-korcula-port-100116 %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bells ringing in Korčula's port&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

The weather was especially beautiful for autumn, and the timing of our visit was perfect. Shops started closing down for the season the day that we left.

## Maksimilijan garden
We walked to Maksimilijan garden on a particularly warm yet breezy day, got a drink, and relaxed by the shore. Bob Marley always seems to be playing in the background in environments such as this, and so it was when we were there. We watched different sizes of boats pass between our island and the next. A wind surfer was out taking advantage of the strong gusts; it looked like a fight with the elements that the person was losing.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

We stopped inside the garden's gallery/museum on our way back toward town. The day we visited was the last before closing for the season. We and two other groups of people were the only ones around.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}

## Around the island
Our ferry to Split wouldn't arrive until about 6pm on our last day, so we decided to rent a car and check out the rest of the island. This proved to be a very memorable experience because of the magnificent scenery and the very narrow roads running alongside precipitous cliffs. We took it all in stride (ha!) in a little VW Polo with a very loose clutch.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-10&quot; %}

The stress of the drive proved itself to be worthwhile. For instance, a handful of hairpin turns down a 1200-foot decline on a one-car road led us to this. On our walk down to the bay, we heard rustling from the bushes and concluded that the only way our drive down could be made more exciting was if we were then charged by a boar. Thankfully, we were not.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-9&quot; %}

Korčula isn't a very big island at about 30 miles long and 5 miles wide, so we followed the main roads from Korčula, the old city, on the east to Vela Luka on the west. We made stops in Lumbarda, Pupnatska Luka (with the hairpin turns), Čara, and Blato. The entire trip took about 4.5 hours, including a stop for coffee and another for lunch.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-11&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-12&quot; %}
{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-13&quot; %}

Once we found what seemed to be the only gas station on the east side of the island and filled up, we returned the car and hung out near the port until our ferry arrived at dusk.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-8&quot; %}

# Coming Soon
Photos from our overnight in [Split](/split).</content><author><name>ECG</name></author><category term="balkan" /><category term="croatia" /><category term="dubrovnik" /><category term="korcula" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Sarajevo to Dubrovnik</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/dubrovnik/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Sarajevo to Dubrovnik" /><published>2016-11-22T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-11-22T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/dubrovnik</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/dubrovnik/"># Goodbye, Sarajevo
Our [taxi driver, Mili,](https://www.facebook.com/mostartaxi/) picked us up in Sarajevo at 8AM. We headed west and then south with an end destination of Dubrovnik. Mili recommended several stops along the way so we could see points in the history of Bosnia as well as the dramatic shift from mountainous to Mediterranean geography and climate.

## Konjić
[Konjić](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konjic) is one of Bosnia's oldest settlements, a sleepy town straddling the Neretva river. Its population is majority Bosniak, though sizeable groups of Croats and Serbs also live there.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

The Neretva is a [karst](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karst) river and provides the area with drinking water as well as hydroelectric power. We followed it all the way to Mostar.

## Jablanica
We stopped in Jablanica so Mili could show us the site of an event famous enough to be worthy of a film: the [Battle of Neretva](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Neretva_(film)). As told to us, [Tito](/balkans/#tito) and his army were trapped against the Neretva by Axis soldiers while trying to save the wounded. Tito had the railway bridges across the river destroyed to trick Axis soldiers into thinking they had fled in a different direction than they actually went. Many of Tito's troops were able to escape due to this move, and Tito's pledge not to leave the wounded behind was maintained.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

As we drove south of Jablanica the mountain forest terrain gave way to Mediterranean; tall trees thinned out and were replaced by vineyards, olive and citrus trees.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

## Mostar
When we left Sarajevo the temperature was around 5°C / 40°F. By the time we arrived in Mostar, it was 28°C / 82°F. Mostar is Mili's hometown, so we parked and he showed us around.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

The photo below on the left was taken in 1993 in Mostar's old city during the Bosnian war. The photo on the right was taken during our walk through the old city area, which was still pretty full of tourists despite it being the end of the major tourist season.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-5&quot; %}

Mili led us off the main path and took us to his in-law's café where we were introduced to the philosophy behind Bosnian coffee, or Bosanska kafa. Behold:

&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot;  href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/kijasek/5874231598/in/photolist-5ECSQ2-AjvtXJ-dVVTar-fK1ej-nmLLcw-9X384i-5y5Q8-fD76Up-8FMnEx-2iacKK-6VYwyn-8Ggs2x-jhHV48-aGMNze-fDRWLj-cL8gc9-4gE7cz-aHwLEH-omeyyz-8Rrquv-946kuh-5BhFMT-8GjDYh-nueauv-4zMo4r-AYstcB-4NCTMQ-4zRC8h-CWTYcm-CRURye-9X5Yp9-943gp6-oiHjYy-vRSzsQ-8GjCud-5FdUfT-6Vwkdf-461ntV-fD76Ev-r7DoPT-a3tFJq-8GjCBL-4NCWBW-bHpX28-8aCKbf-943dTa-6q5cfn-RRN4c-LLsyHk-FLy7TL&quot; title=&quot;bosnian coffee in Sarajevo&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://c7.staticflickr.com/4/3116/5874231598_b7c7f22c08_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;768&quot; alt=&quot;bosnian coffee in Sarajevo&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

Mili's brother-in-law emphasized that the purpose of Bosnian coffee was to give one time to reset or reflect. You wake up, consider all the things you have to do, and then think &quot;but first, coffee&quot; and allow yourself 15 minutes to pause before starting the day. It's also something to be taken with friends so that you can enjoy and share time with each other.

The preparation of Bosanska kafa is similar to Turkish coffee but Bosnians emphasize that it is also very different. I'm the wrong person to educate you on those nuances. I can, however, share the coffee-making steps we were given:

1. Put extra finely ground coffee into a coffee pot (džezva) at a ratio of 1-2 teaspoons per serving
2. Pour about 2 ounces of boiling water per serving over the grounds and stir
3. Put over heat and bring to a boil once (versus three times for Turkish coffee)
4. Pour a few spoons of cold water over the top of the coffee to help pull the grounds in the foam down to the bottom; this should also help make crema, which our guide referred to as the best part of the coffee
5. Use a spoon to scrape loose any remaining grounds around the rim of the coffee pot
6. Spoon a little bit of the crema into each cup
7. Slowly pour the coffee, being careful not to tip the pot so far as to pour a bunch of grounds into the cups; some will inevitably make it in anyway, and that's perfectly fine if you sip slowly
{: .notice}


According to Mili's brother-in-law, Bosnian coffee is not prepared with sugar in the pot or in the cups. Rather, you dip a sugar cube into the coffee, take a small bite off of it, and then hold the sugar on your tongue while drinking so that the coffee is sweetened en route. I don't take sugar with mine, but I do love rahat lokum (essentially Turkish delight) which is served alongside the coffee. Rosewater is a traditional flavor served with coffee. Our guide to Srebrenica took us to a shop in Sarajevo and bought us several other varieties to try. My favorite thus far is pistachio with shredded coconut.

After coffee we started toward Dubrovnik.

## Drive to Dubrovnik

Mili knew of a border crossing that had recently been opened to tourists and wasn't as heavily trafficked as the main route into Dubrovnik. This was estimated to save us anywhere from one to several hours of wait time at the border. The drive isn't one I would have done myself— the roads were windy, steep, and narrow—though the views as we went from mountain roads to flat farmland were really stunning.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-6&quot; %}

As Mili had promised, our transition from Bosnia to Croatia was quick and uneventful. We drove on more windy, steep, and narrow roads that ran us alongside the Adriatic sea and eventually delivered us to our hotel near the Dubrovnik port.

After we settled in, we took a taxi to the old city, had dinner, went to the [War Photo Limited](http://www.warphotoltd.com/) museum, and then enjoyed a sunset drink along the city wall.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-7&quot; %}

# Coming Soon
Photos and stories from [Korčula](/korcula).

# Reading List
I'll go light on the reading recommendations this time. Do check out [War Photo Limited](http://www.warphotoltd.com/) for photos from different wars as well as books such as [Broken Lights of Yugoslavia, Emmanuel Ortiz](http://www.warphotoltd.com/shop/books/broken-lights-of-yugoslavia7).</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Srebrenica</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-srebrenica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Srebrenica" /><published>2016-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-srebrenica</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-srebrenica/"># Into Republika Srpska
Bosnia has two autonomous entities: the Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina (BiH) and Republika Srpska (RS). Sarajevo is within the Federation of BiH, and Srebrenica is in Republika Srpska. There are no border crossings between these regions, so the best way to tell which you're in is by looking at the road signs; the Federation of BiH uses the Latin alphabet, and Republika Srpska uses Cyrillic. Republika Srpska is predominantly Serb, and the Federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina is mostly Bosniak to the north, Croat to the south.

On September 25th, the tour group consisted of Rachel and me, so our guide drove us two-and-a-half hours northeast to the [Srebrenica Genocide Memorial](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Srebrenica_Genocide_Memorial). We passed from the Federation region into Republika Srpska without ceremony.

The fog was heavy as we wound through the mountains of the [Dinaric Alps](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinaric_Alps). The forests were thick and felt very old. I have never seen terrain like what we drove through that day. There weren't many places to stop and take photos, and I didn't feel right taking any in the car while talking with our guide. He was substituting for his brother who was unable to make it at the last moment. He seemed tense, so we talked about 90s hip hop and the movies he watched to teach himself English.

We turned off onto a smaller country road and wound through farm land. The fog was thick until late in the morning. Conversation about US pop culture naturally turned to questions about our current presidential election, and our guide posited that the area we were driving through was one that would likely vote for Trump. He then pointed at a flock of sheep and said they would vote for him, too, and baahed &quot;Truuuuump!&quot; We didn't get much deeper into the conversation than that. It was enough.

## Referendum day
A while later, our guide apologized for driving slowly and explained that that day was referendum day in Republika Srpska and he wanted to be careful. A contentious vote was being held to determine whether the region would declare its own national day (separate from the rest of the country) on the date of its founding in 1992. Bosnia-Herzegovina's constitutional court had declared the referendum unconstitutional for discriminating against Bosniaks and Croatians, but the region proceeded with the referendum anyway.

Our guide was a Bosniak and noted that the police are predominantly Serb, so he didn't want to risk getting pulled over. He pointed out the Serbian flags hanging from homes and on fences as we continued driving. It reminded me of the Confederate flags I grew up seeing hung on porches and in the backs of trucks, and it made me feel a similar kind of discomfort. I understand why he didn't want to attract unnecessary attention.

The referendum was an act of defiance against the unified state of Bosnia-Herzegovina. Republika Srpska's president, [Milorad Dodik](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milorad_Dodik) is a huge proponent of [seceding from Bosnia-Herzegovina](https://iwpr.net/global-voices/nationalist-talk-ahead-bosnian-local-polls) and has promised to hold a referendum to decide on that in 2018. Most believe it's unlikely to occur since Republika Srpska, though backed by Russia, lacks broader international support. If they were to succeed, it would effectively destroy the peace accords established in Dayton.

# Srebrenica
The Srebrenica Genocide Memorial, or Srebrenica-Potočari Memorial and Cemetery for the Victims of the 1995 Genocide officially, is tucked between the mountains in a broad valley about 10km outside of the city of Srebrenica itself. The museum was closed on the day we were there due to the referendum, so we walked around the cemetery in relative quiet. There were many places where visitors could sit alone and reflect or gather together and pray.

![](/assets/images/travel/srebrenica/srebrenica-pano.jpg)
{: .center}
&lt;figcaption&gt;50,000 people; 300 UN soldiers to protect against 5,000 militia; over 8,000 men and boys killed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

Rachel and our guide were both using the restroom when I saw cars with Serbian flags driving by and honking their horns, likely in celebration of the referendum.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

As we looked over the wall of names of those buried, our guide noted that the date of death indicated on the tombstones reflects the year that person's death was actually confirmed; people whose death years were more recent didn't necessarily die then. That's just when their remains were identified.

It's been over 20 years since the massacre. They're still digging and finding bodies.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

It was especially difficult to see birth years that were the same as our own and imagine being in any one of their positions at 13 or 14 years old. I cannot imagine how it could have felt to learn that a man known as the Butcher of Bosnia, [Ratko Mladić](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ratko_Mladi%C4%87), and the Bosnian Serb Army of Republika Srpska (VRS) had promised to return Srebrenica to the Serbs and [&quot;take revenge upon the Turks in this region.&quot;](http://www.srebrenica360.com/#/panorama?id=p9) Nor can I imagine how it must have felt to be part of the 25,000 refugees gathered at Potočari awaiting evacuation in July 1995 when Mladić and his army began their attack and United Nations forces [repeatedly failed to provide protection](http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/16/world/un-details-its-failure-to-stop-95-bosnia-massacre.html).

Thinking about it for too long makes it hard to believe in the goodwill of others, particularly as we come up on the most divisive US election cycle I've personally experienced. Humankind repeats itself regularly enough for me to see obvious behavioral patterns between the Bosnian War and what's happening in the US and parts of Europe today:

* Social, ethnic, and racial tensions exacerbated by the rhetoric of demagogues
* Violent language resulting in violent actions
* Families and friends turning against each other based on differences like race, ethnicity, and religion
* The defining of &quot;us&quot; as human and &quot;them&quot; as less-than-human and thus undeserving of respect, protection, and even life

It's very important for us to pay attention to the mistakes of our collective past and work together to avoid repeating them.

This election is really, really important, but especially for Bosnian Americans because we have seen what hate speech can do in a country. Some of the older ones are scared, because this is a similar thing going on back in Bosnia in the 1990s before the election.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;_Ibro Tucakovic in [&quot;How Missouri's 'Bosnian vote​' could cost Donald Trump – and turn the state blue&quot;](https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/sep/04/bosnian-muslim-vote-missouri-republican-donald-trump)_
{: .notice}

# Return Trip
We ate lunch in Srebrenica then headed back toward Sarajevo and talked about lighter things. We learned that our guide dislikes vegetables, but especially hates buranija (string beans). A roadside stand was advertising buranija, and our guide didn't know the English word for the vegetable, so he described them: very common at holiday functions, their parts can be separated and used in different types of dishes, and &quot;you eat them and then you throw it back up.&quot;

When talking about Bosnian politics, our guide quoted his favorite rapper to explain the process: [&quot;it's all about the benjamins.&quot;](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNTBb1u6UGg) It seems our political systems aren't so different after all!

Our guide to Srebrenica is 30, so he was about 10 when he and his family returned to Sarajevo through Tunel Spasa for his father. He lived through war, as his parents, grandparents, and great-grandparents all had. While acknowledging historic tensions between ethnic groups, he joked that, because his wife was half Croatian, half-Serb and he was Bosniak, they got to celebrate three times as many holidays. He also pointed out his home as we walked back into the old city in Sarajevo and took us to the candy shop with the best [lokum](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_delight) so he could buy some for us before we parted ways.

We had a lot of time to talk, and it was apparent that many of the things he has lived through were difficult to discuss, but he shared a part of himself with Rachel and me that day nonetheless. There is no more effective way to learn from and empathize with others than through the sharing of stories and time. My view of the world has been impacted by that which he shared with us. I hope that we contributed something new and positive to his worldview, as well.

# Coming Soon
Photos and stories from our drive to [Dubrovnik](/dubrovnik).

# Reading List
Joe Sacco wrote a graphic novel on another UN-designated safe area attacked during the Bosnian war.
* [Safe Area Goražde: The War in Eastern Bosnia 1992-1995](http://amzn.to/2cZxgUF)

Additional reading on Srebrenica and Republika Srpska's latest referendum:
* [Srebrenica Virtual Museum](http://www.srebrenica.org.uk/resources/srebrenica-virtual-museum/)
* [A Referendum by Serbs Threatens Yet More Trouble for Bosnia](http://www.economist.com/news/europe/21707877-banned-vote-separate-bosnian-serb-national-day-has-some-people-talking-war-referendum)
* [Bosnian Serbs Greenlight Saudi Grant for Srebrenica](http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/bosnian-serbs-greenlight-saudi-grant-for-srebrenica-10-28-2016)
* [Srebrenica Votes Recounted as Bosniaks Seek Annulment](http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/srebrenica-recount-begins-as-bosniak-party-seeks-annulment-10-11-2016)
* [Bosnia, Donald Trump, And What We Should Have Learned By Now](https://www.bustle.com/articles/150041-bosnia-donald-trump-and-what-we-should-have-learned-by-now)
* [Biggest Serb party in Bosnia threatens 2018 secession](http://www.reuters.com/article/us-bosnia-serbs-secession-idUSKBN0NG0NB20150425)
* [Is War About to Break Out in the Balkans?](http://foreignpolicy.com/2015/10/26/war-break-out-balkans-bosnia-republika-srpska-dayton/)
* [Is This the Beginning of a Bosnian Spring?](http://www.vice.com/en_uk/read/bosnia-tuzla-sarajevo-protests-bosnianspring-daytonaccords)</content><author><name>ECG</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="conflict" /><category term="nationalism" /><category term="politics" /><category term="balkan" /><category term="bosnia" /><category term="srebrenica" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Sarajevo</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-sarajevo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Sarajevo" /><published>2016-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-sarajevo</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/bosnia-sarajevo/"># Welcome to Sarajevo
We landed in Sarajevo in the evening and took in a view of the surrounding mountains at dusk while waiting to go through customs. Cigarette smoke wafted in the air. Though travel forums suggested we could, neither of us were able to find a place in the airport to buy a local SIM card, so we went to the taxi stand, I gave the driver the address of our apartment, and we were off.

The drive from the airport to the old city where we were staying was about twenty minutes. Cars are restricted within the main portion of the old city, so the driver dropped us off as close to the heart of it as he could. He then admitted he didn't know where the actual address of our apartment was, so we found a police officer, and he recruited the help of another person. They told us it was walkable but uphill and suggested we take another cab there, so we did. That was the right decision.

**Pro Tip**: &lt;br /&gt;Print a map of directions to your apartment prior to traveling to a place you know you'll be without phone/data service. Flat-landers, check the topographic view of the area to better understand what you're getting into.
{: .notice}

I rang the bell for the wrong apartment, woke a friendly-sounding British person, and then shone my light on the panel only to discover a faint &quot;Airbnb&quot; written beside the buzzer right below the one I rang. Once settled, we rejoiced at Rachel's brilliant plan to save the mini-bottles of wine handed out on our flight for this very moment: our adventure in the Balkans had begun.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-1&quot; %}

We sat on our porch every morning and evening to listen to sounds of the city like this:

{% archive_audio call-to-prayer %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Calls to prayer in Sarajevo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We only had four days in Sarajevo, and one was to be spent in Srebrenica, so we dove right in the next day.

# Siege
A difficult ethnic history will not, by itself, necessarily cause the loss of hundreds of thousands of lives in conditions resembling the Holocaust. For that calamity, one needs additional factors: Western confusion and inaction which, in turn, create a power vacuum. Without these other elements, the horrors of the 1990s might not have occurred.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
_Kaplan, Robert D. (2014-04-01). Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History (Kindle Locations 86-88). Picador. Kindle Edition._
{: .notice}

We went on a tour of several places within and around the city to learn about the siege by Serbian forces, which started in 1992.

You don't have to use much imagination to feel the loss Sarajevo has experienced. Row after row of tombstones fill hillsides and are wedged in between homes and in parks. Some tombs are from the time of the Ottoman Empire; most dates fall between 1992 and 1996.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-4&quot; %}

Loss is an obvious part of the city and the people's identity; so are defiance and resilience. The [siege of Sarajevo](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Sarajevo) lasted nearly four years. On average, nearly 330 bombs were dropped per day in an effort to break the morale of those within the city. Snipers were spread out around the 70 kilometer siege perimeter, and supply lines into the city were cut or constrained. In response, Sarajevans used guerilla warfare to combat their opponents, and the [Tunel Spasa](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarajevo_Tunnel) was built to transport people and goods in and out of the city.

![](/assets/images/travel/sarajevo/sarajevo-cemetery-pano.jpg)
{: .center}
&lt;figcaption&gt;We passed the war cemetery every time we went out; every day the sunrise and sunset were breathtaking. Enjoying something beautiful while simultaneously feeling sad about such a significant loss is complicated. &lt;/figcaption&gt;

## A little background
In this region, one's ethnicity determines their expected religious affiliation. Bosniaks are Muslim, Croats are Catholic, and Serbs are Orthodox. Today, each major ethnic group in the country is represented by a democratically elected president, legislative, judicial, and local officials. This was the structure defined by the [Dayton Accords](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dayton_Agreement). The Dayton Agreement was established as the transitional constitution for Bosnia-Herzegovina (BiH); it is still in place today, as a new constitution has not been agreed upon.

Our guide noted that the presidents of BiH must agree unanimously in order to enact new laws or create a new constitution. This makes it nearly impossible for anything to get done. Much of the population's focus is therefore on local efforts. He emphasized that people make things happen and that they had given up on government.

Nothing seemed overtly tense during our time in Sarajevo. Both of our guides' perspectives were that Bosniaks, Croats, and Serbs lived together quite well prior to the war and that nationalism is what broke them apart. They used the proximity of old Catholic, Jewish, Muslim, and Orthodox places of worship as an historic example of peaceful coexistence.

# Old City
We liked exploring the old city early in the day when it wasn't as busy, but the energy of the area when the streets are filled with shop owners, cafe-goers, pigeon-feeders, and people-watchers was warm and electric.

**Listen**:
{% archive_audio come-on-down-barhana %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Music playing at Barhana cafe at lunchtime&lt;/figcaption&gt;

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-2&quot; %}

We saw a broad range of liberal and conservative religious folks, all intermingling within the old city. Sarajevo itself feels more secular. From the people we spoke to, it seems that, much like in the US, many people associate with a religion (primarily based on culture/ethnicity) and observe religious holidays but are otherwise neutral.

# Walking tour
The city's full of interesting little details, so we explored and found indications of the area's Austro-Hungarian, Ottoman, Capitalist, and Communist influences. A little bit of something for everyone, really. Check out the details in each photo for more information.

{% include gallery id=&quot;gallery-3&quot; %}

After all that walking, imagine sitting down in a bar filled with artifacts from different places and times, ordering a drink, and listening to this:
{% archive_audio goldfish-bar-sarajevo %}
&lt;figcaption&gt;Music playing at Zlatna ribica (goldfish) bar&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It was the perfect ending to our day and time in Sarajevo.

# Coming Soon
Photos and stories from our day trip to [Srebrenica](/bosnia-srebrenica).

# Further Reading
For a little bit different take on Bosnia, Sarajevo, and the war, check out Joe Sacco's graphic novels.
* [The Fixer: A Story from Sarajevo](http://amzn.to/2dezxyF)
* [War's End: Profiles from Bosnia, 1995-1996](http://amzn.to/2cBgPil)

Additional reading on Bosnia and politics:
* [Bosnia - Voting for the Devil You Know](http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/blog/bosnia-voting-for-the-devil-you-know-1)
* [Opinion: Bosnia's EU Application](https://jessiehronesova.wordpress.com/2016/01/20/bosnias-eu-application-political-ruse-or-misguided-optimism/)
* [Opinion: EU and Western Balkans](https://jessiehronesova.wordpress.com/2016/01/14/eu-and-western-balkans/)
* [Disputes Delay Publication of Bosnia Census](http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/disputes-delay-publication-of-bosnia-census-11-04-2015)
* [Bosnia and Herzegovina: the world's most complicated system of government?](https://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/2014/oct/08/bosnia-herzegovina-elections-the-worlds-most-complicated-system-of-government)</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">The Balkans: Introduction</title><link href="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/balkans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Balkans: Introduction" /><published>2016-10-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-10-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/balkans</id><content type="html" xml:base="//elisabethgrayme.firebaseapp.com/balkans/"># Introduction
My wife, Rachel, and I recently traveled to the Balkans. We intentionally chose Sarajevo as the starting point for our visit, which _may_ have had something to do with my obsession with the history of the city and surrounding region.

The Bosnian war was happening when I was in middle-high school. It's where and when my interest in media technology’s role in conflict and the definition of cultural/nationalist identities began. In high school, I wrote a paper expressing my naive distress about a world which had allowed genocide to occur yet again. Over the past 20 years I've continued to watch, read, and [write](/academics/never-again) about the Balkans, Bosnia-Herzegovina in particular.

The breakup of Yugoslavia affords us an opportunity to look at our own cultural and nationalistic identities and imagine potential outcomes. Sarajevo is a beautiful and solemn monument to the volatility of peace and the complexity of identity. I'll talk about this more in upcoming posts, but if that isn't your particular cup of tea, stick around! I'll also share entertaining things about our trip. But first, a brief foray into the history of the former Yugoslavia, which should help future references make a bit more sense.

#  Crash Course in Modern South Balkan History

## Yugoslavia
[Yugoslavia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yugoslavia), or Jugoslavija, comes from the combination of the Croatian word 'jug' for 'south' and 'slaveni' to indicate a people of Slavic descent. It started out as a kingdom of former territories of Austria-Hungary and the Ottoman Empire, post-World War I. The Serbian royal family was the Yugoslav royal dynasty.

## World War II
During World War II, the country was occupied by Axis forces and divided up into parts: Croatia, Bosnia, Herzegovina, Serbia, and Slovenia. Nationalist factions developed within these subdivisions of the country, and two resistance forces arose in opposition to Axis occupation: the [Yugoslav Partisans](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yugoslav_Partisans), led by [Josip Broz Tito](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josip_Broz_Tito), and the [Chetniks](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chetniks) who were decidedly pro-Serbian and eventually turned against the Partisans. The Partisans succeeded in freeing Yugoslavia from Axis powers in 1945, abolished the Serbian royal family and government, and made Yugoslavia a communist state.

&lt;a name=&quot;tito&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

## Josip Broz Tito
Josip Broz Tito was the leader of the Partisans. His Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia existed until 1990 and was comprised of six republics known today as Bosnia-Herzegovina, Croatia, Macedonia, Montenegro, Slovenia, and Serbia, plus the autonomous provinces of Vojvodina and Kosovo.

![former-yugoslavia](https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a9/Former_Yugoslavia_Map.png)
&lt;figcaption align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href = &quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a9/Former_Yugoslavia_Map.png&quot;&gt;sourced from Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
The people we met on our trip spoke with varying degrees of enthusiasm about Tito's leadership. Most admitted that they had never directly experienced Tito's Yugoslavia because they were too young, but general sentiment toward him skewed positive. He was an authoritarian ruler, yes, but one that maintained peace and provided stability. Those who [criticized him](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yugoslavia#Government) weren't guaranteed the same protections.

Locals put a lot of emphasis on the fact that Tito's version of communism was different than that of Stalinist Russia. Tito did, in fact, break with Stalin in 1948, and Yugoslavia became an independent communist state. He aligned with [other countries](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-Aligned_Movement) that wanted a system somewhere in between the capitalism of the West and communism of the East.

## Ethnic tension
When Tito's party took over leadership of Yugoslavia, nationalism was banned from being publicly promoted, but protestors voiced concerns that Yugoslavia was still a Serb hegemony. In 1974, Tito responded in part by reducing Serbian influence through the creation of autonomous regions: Kosovo and Vojvodina. The new regions appeased groups concerned with Serbs' influence and consequently upset Serbs, whose political position was diminished. Autonomous regions were given the same voting capability as republics but differed from them in one major way: they could not separate from Yugoslavia, whereas republics technically had the right to secede (this detail is important later).

## Economic downturn
The price of oil dropped in the 1970s and triggered an economic crisis in Yugoslavia. Debt increased and demand for Yugoslavian products decreased. Unemployment rose. I suspect we're all familiar with the kind of discomfort these economic changes can cause in a society.

## Death of Tito
Tito died in 1980, and an eight-member council of representatives—one for each republic and autonomous region—replaced him. Ethnic tensions rose again. Kosovo wanted to be recognized as a republic rather than an autonomous entity, and Serbs were becoming increasingly frustrated with their inability to pass legislation, despite being the largest ethnic group in Yugoslavia.

## Slobodan Milošević
Milošević was the council member representing Serbia. He wanted to make Serbia great again by restoring its sovereignty. From 1986 to 1989, he successfully destabilized the governments of Montenegro, Vojvodina, and Kosovo and replaced existing leaders with his allies. This significantly reduced Vojvodina and Kosovo's autonomy and secured four guaranteed votes in the council, including one for Serbia.

In 1987, an ambitious Serbian Communist party leader, Slobodan Milosevic...pointed his finger in the distance— at what Mother Tatiana had labeled out there— and, as legend now has it, pledged: “They’ll never do this to you again. Never again will anyone defeat you.”
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At that moment, as the crowd roared, the Serbian revolt against the Yugoslav federation began; it soon spread laterally to the other republics. One by one, Serbs gathered the courage to remove the fearful icon of Tito from their homes and shops, replacing it with a photo of the plump, baby-faced Milosevic. The only Eastern European Communist leader in the late 1980s who managed to save himself and his party from collapse did so by making a direct appeal to racial hatred.
&lt;br/&gt;  
_Kaplan, Robert D. (2014-04-01). Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History (Kindle Locations 1281-1287). Picador. Kindle Edition._
{: .notice}

## The breakup of Yugoslavia
Ethnic Albanians in Kosovo organized strikes in 1989, and those turned into broader demonstrations demanding Kosovo be recognized as a republic. In early 1990, the [League of Communists of Yugoslavia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/League_of_Communists_of_Yugoslavia) convened. Milošević and the Serbian delegates argued in favor of a &quot;one person, one vote&quot; policy which would benefit the Serb-majority within Yugoslavia. Slovenian and Croatian delegates pushed for greater power within the republics and were voted down. They then left the Congress; the Communist party of Yugoslavia was dissolved.

## Yugoslav Wars
Yugoslavia did not deteriorate suddenly, but gradually and methodically, step by step, through the 1980s, becoming poorer and meaner and more hate-filled by the year. That’s why every conversation I had was so sad. We were all shouting to the outside world about a coming catastrophe, but no one wanted to hear our awful secret. No one was interested.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
_Kaplan, Robert D. (2014-04-01). Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History (Kindle Locations 716-718). Picador. Kindle Edition._
{: .notice}

Nationalistic stances took rise as Slovenia and Croatia continued to loosen their ties to the Federation. War broke out when the republics tried to replace Yugoslav civilian and military forces with secessionist ones.

In mid-1991, Slovenia and Croatia both declared independence from Yugoslavia. Slovenia's war for independence lasted [ten days](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ten-Day_War), whereas the [Croatian](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croatian_War_of_Independence) and [Bosnian](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_War) wars for independence took over four years. The differences in war durations are related (in part) to a higher number of ethnic Serbs living in Croatia and Bosnia-Herzegovina than in Slovenia. Serbs opposed the countries' secessions from Yugoslavia and wanted Serb-majority areas of the countries to remain in a common state with Serbia. Serbs voted in November 1991 to form a Serbian republic within the borders of Bosnia-Herzegovina in order to do just that, and in January 1992 they announced a separate Republika Srpska. Just over a month later, Bosnia-Herzegovina declared its independence from Yugoslavia. Bosnian Serbs rejected the referendum and declared Republika Srpska's independence from Bosnia-Herzegovina on April 5th; the Bosnian war officially started the following day.

# Further Reading
There's a whole lot more to the story! A lot of specifics were skipped if they weren't directly relevant to the account of our trip. If you want to learn more about the region, actors, or wars, I recommend taking a look at what Wikipedia has to offer. It's relatively clear and concise and can send you spiraling blissfully down a rabbit hole of information if you dig into the citations. I've included links to some such pages in the text above.

I'm currently reading [Black Lamb and Grey Falcon](http://amzn.to/2dyABZ5), and [Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism](http://amzn.to/2ehS4ci). I've enjoyed what I've read thus far. I've also read and recommend checking out these books if you're interested in going deeper into this subject:

* [The Sleepwalkers: How Europe Went to War in 1914](http://amzn.to/2di1nWy)
* [Balkan Ghosts: A Journey Through History](http://amzn.to/2dpzyMy)
* [War Is a Force That Gives Us Meaning](http://amzn.to/2cBhfoK)

# Coming Soon
I'll share photos and stories from:

* **Bosnia**: [Sarajevo](/bosnia-sarajevo), [Srebrenica](/bosnia-srebrenica), and [the trip south through Mostar](/dubrovnik)
* **Croatia**: [Dubrovnik](/dubrovnik), [Korčula](/korcula), [Split](/split), [Plitvice lakes](/plitvice), and [Zagreb](/zagreb)
* **Slovenia**: [Ljubljana](/slovenia/#ljubljana), [Vintgar gorge](/slovenia/#vintgar-gorge), [Lake Bled](/slovenia/#lake-bled), and [Hiša Franko](/slovenia/#hiša-franko)
* **Italy**: [Venice](/venice)</content><author><name>ECG</name></author></entry></feed>